<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Python | Avi Das]]></title>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/categories/python/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-05-07T13:14:32-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://avidas.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Avi (Ananya Das)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pycon Canada 2015 II: Python for Reliably Delivering Cross Platform Products]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2015/11/24/pycon-canada-2015-ii-python-for-reliably-delivering-cross-platform-products/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-24T20:41:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2015/11/24/pycon-canada-2015-ii-python-for-reliably-delivering-cross-platform-products</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the second part of the two series blog post about my talk at PyCon Canada. Here is the <a href="http://aviadas.com/blog/2015/11/21/pycon-canada-2015-speaking-at-my-first-conference/">first part</a>.</p>

<h3>Proposal:</h3>

<p>Are you part of a team responsible for delivering cross platform products? End to end automated testing and communicating effectively are important when your project depends on multiple teams spread across functional domains. At Braintree/PayPal, we worked on a framework to reliably ship developer facing products. We will go over using BDD with Behave to describe test scenarios that speaks to both product and engineering, using Appium for mobile automation, and ElasicSearch and Kibana for storage and visualization of test results. You will see how the breadth of packages available on PyPI, the flexibility and ease of Python helped a team of developers whose core competencies were not in Python to collaborate on a common ground.</p>

<h3>Slides:</h3>

<p><iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/55489167 " width="595" height="446" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen></iframe> </p>

<h3>Video:</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YnCtm3ZDynY">Youtube link</a></p>

<h3>Github Repo</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/avidas/reliability-demo">Reliability Demo</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at PyCon Canada 2015: I]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2015/11/21/pycon-canada-2015-speaking-at-my-first-conference/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-21T12:38:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2015/11/21/pycon-canada-2015-speaking-at-my-first-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>High Level Takeaways</h3>

<ul>
<li>If you are giving a talk, too much content on slides means the audience is reading the slides instead of listening to you.</li>
<li>Design your talk expecting failure, and assume things like wifi will not work. An analogy would be the non functional escalator still being a staircase.</li>
<li>Show your talk to as many people as time allows. Every time I showed my talk to someone, I would find a new way to make the talk better.</li>
<li>It was amazing to hear from a 10 year old about his experience in coding. The barrier to entry to tech will keep falling in a noticeable way.</li>
<li>Teaching remains the best way to learn alongside with building things.</li>
<li>Coding for expectability is often as important as any considerations in a software project.</li>
<li>Science, data, web, systems and infrastructure were dominant themes at PyCon.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Getting to Toronto</h3>

<ul>
<li>It was really exciting to have my talk accepted at PyCon, since it was my first time speaking at a conference.</li>
<li>Getting through customs went as painless as they could have.</li>
<li>Toronto was colder than Austin, big surprise! Reminded me of times back in East Coast.</li>
<li>T-mobile data roaming was a breeze to set up, and worked mostly well across different providers.</li>
<li>Toronto had different modes of public transportation getting from downtown to airport: buses, streetcars, subway. Makes a city more interesting, although makes day to day travelling more complicated. Although, it does not take a whole lot to put public transportation in Austin to shame.</li>
<li>Asked a lady on the Subway for directions. It soon turned into a great conversation with her and her husband about life in Toronto and their experiences in US. For a big city, Toronto scores major points for having friendly people. Canadians have a reputation of being polite and helpful, and I would come to recognize it throughout my trip there.</li>
<li>My AirBnB was in Kensington Market, close to UoT where PyCon was taking place. It was a vibrant neighborhood, bars, restaurants, transportation nearby. My room was no hotel room, but a bed was all I needed.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Saturday</h3>

<ul>
<li>Morning started with me feeling the stress of not having all my slides and examples ready. I wanted to take some time to reflect on the great feedback I got from my team, but there was little time left.</li>
<li>Adding to my anxiety was the wifi connection not working. Thankfully, some organizers helped me out. Once the certificate issues resolved, it worked well for remainder of the conference.</li>
<li>Continental breakfast consisted of an assortment of cottage cheese, granola/yogurt, muffins, bread and coffee. No complaints.</li>
<li>Talked to Dusty, a Facebook engineer working on the Facebook infrastructure in Portland. Having lived in Canada, he had a lot to share about his experience there.</li>
<li>Morning keynote explored the history of Python interpreters and went into benchmarks. Benchmark related conversations can get subjective, but the speaker did a good job avoiding that.</li>
<li>Talks on application security, Emmy nominated CGI(!) and Docker deployment followed. The CGI talk was offered a very different viewpoint in software problems. Being highly computation intensive and long life cycles means the tradeoffs are very different from the usual SASS app/consumer product.</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li>Fully vegetarian lunch would have made some of my friends in Austin very happy.</li>
<li>Talks on code quality and scaling followed in the afternoon. The scaling talk did not cover scaling a python service, but rather maintaining OpenStack, in the order of 4-5 million lines of code written in Python.</li>
<li>SaltStack for deployment and fraud detection were next on the agenda. Fraud is very relevant for those in the payments industry, so I was very interested in the talk. Most of the talk focused on Apache Spark, and the fraud aspects covered some of the usual signals such as checking location of IP against location of the credit card.</li>
<li>Karen Rubin's ending keynote was the highlight of the day. As a director in Quantopian, she benchmarked placing bets on companies with female CEOs and bet them against the S&amp;500. She presented her initial model, and presented various tunings to her model. Factoring in arbitrage during the initial period when a female CEO got brought in, divergence due to outliers such as Meg Whitman or Marissa Mayer, and female CEOs brought on to replace poorly performing male CEOs were some of the considerations. Even with all, her strategy still handily beat the S&amp;P500! This makes one wonder how segmenting CEOs further by backgrounds would perform against the market.</li>
<li>At the end of the day, I got to talk to some engineers from Dropbox and Heroku. Pain points with experiences doing online payments came up, when the tradeoff was unfortunately often to trade integration pain points with services more susceptible to fraud.</li>
<li>Over dinner, I chatted with a core group who have grown the Python meetup scene in Toronto from a handful of people to a conference with many hundreds of people today. We talked about their efforts in teaching Python to children and disparity on expectations as a software engineer based on location and industry.</li>
<li>In the evening, I spent more time going through the presentation, trying to replace more slides with workflow diagrams.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Sunday</h3>

<ul>
<li>Sunday was the day of my talk. The day started later than first, and I took full advantage by going for a run around downtown Toronto. As I ran by the CN tower and the financial district, the tourist density went up significantly. It was a colder morning, but running in a new city is a tradition.</li>
<li>Greenroom at PyCon Toronto very wisely offered speakers the chance to check on their presentation before the actual event. There were issues with fonts, color schemes, and terminal positioning that I was happy to discover. The talk would switch between terminal, emulator, sublime text and slides. I had to make sure that the transition would be as smooth as possible.</li>
<li>It was great to run into old acquaintances from NYC, James Powell of dontusethiscode fame, and Paul Longston. Both are doing terrific things for the Python community.</li>
<li>Morning talks were heavy on REST, Django and Web. One unfortunate thing about speaking at a conference is that you can miss some interesting talks. I definitely would have checked out the other talk given in my time slot on legacy code by Scott Triglia, an Yelp engineer. But that's what videos are for!</li>
<li>It was time for my presentation, with a good number of people in the audience. Checked in with Gabriel, the host at my room. After mike and projector check, it was time. Here we go.</li>
<li>During my talk, I focused on slowing down and focusing on the audience instead of the slides. The demos worked as well as I could have expected! Having the commands stored in the terminal which I could Ctrl+R through avoided a lot of potential issues. One issue that came up was spacing issues in the terminal. As far as things that could have gone wrong, that was a minor one.</li>
<li>Talk lasted for about 29 minutes, and I was pretty happy to get a couple questions at the end. Someone reached out and mentioned that the whole setup was awesome. It was very relieving to have it finally be over and feel the sense of closure.</li>
<li>As a productivity junkie, the afternoon talk on deliberate practice and learning to code was a great one. How can we better realize if we are actually practicing deliberately? It raised some compelling discussion at the end.</li>
<li>At the end of the conference, it was great to see the organizers taking some time to do some well earned celebration.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Part II</h3>

<ul>
<li>I intend to do a followup blog post with the contents of my talk, so stay tuned!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Evaluating React.js and Flask]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2015/08/05/evaluating-react-dot-js-and-flask/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-05T10:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2015/08/05/evaluating-react-dot-js-and-flask</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Update: Udemy has generously granted a free coupon for the readers of this blog for their <a href="https://www.udemy.com/learn-and-understand-reactjs/learn/">React JS and Flux</a> course. Use the code <code>avidasreactjs</code> and the first 50 readers will get free access to the course!</p></blockquote>

<p>As a connoisseur of the web, front-end frameworks have been been a fertile area of late. React.js from Facebook has taken much fanfare, and this post evaluates key ideas on react, and digs into why you could be interested in React. Staying true to single responsibility principle, React is a highly useful tool if you are doing web programming.</p>

<p>In this post, we will dive into building a Frontend using React.js and Backend built using the Python framework Flask. Flask is a minimalistic framework, and excellent when your backend becomes more and more of an API. Moreover, this facilitates the microservices architecture, where the decoupling of your your app into small unit of services can make it more maintainable and scalable.</p>

<p>We will cover some of the key ideas of React and Flask here, but it would be worth referring to the official documentation for <a href="https://facebook.github.io/react/">React</a> and <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/">Flask</a> for getting started and understanding the philosophies of each framework.</p>

<h3>Key Ideas of React</h3>

<p>The core idea of React is the developers are better of leaving manipulating the DOM to battle tested framework code. Since the DOM has a tree structure, finding elements and manipulating them would need many traversals of a potentially very large tree.  Instead, what you modify is a virtual DOM, and React runs its intelligent diffing algorithm to directly update the DOM.</p>

<h5>React</h5>

<p>React itself is the UI library that will manage all the DOM updates as data changes. It's takes the V of MVC frameworks, hence it can be used with other MVC frameworks such as Angular, Backbone or Meteor. It is quite easy to use React to manage specific areas of your application's UI, rather than the entire app.</p>

<h5>Virtual Dom</h5>

<p>The virtual Dom is an abstraction layer between nodes in the real DOM and the view of the code you are modifying. When React selectively renders subtrees of the nodes in DOM based upon state changes, it achieves the following</p>

<pre><code> 1. Ensures that your DOM is always up to date with current state
 2. Reduces the need to re-render the DOM every time there is change in state
 3. Updating only the individual components on state change ensures high performance
</code></pre>

<h5>JSX</h5>

<p>JSX is a JavaScript syntax extension and it brings in a HTML/XML like familiar syntax for defining a tree structure with attributes. This is the syntax you can use to declare the changes in layout code and React will update the UI. It's a bold approach, since developers are conditioned to keep layout code separate from Javascript. We will explain more React terminology later as we dive into some code.</p>

<h3>Key Ideas of Flask</h3>

<p>Flask is a microframework, which means that it trades a short learning curve for fewer out of the box functionalities, compared to heavier frameworks such as Django or Rails. It gives developers more freedom to use their preferable tools and libraries. However, it does have a list of officially supported <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/extensions/">extensions</a> which when plugged in provide a wide breath of functionalities for a standard web app. Extensions behave as if they are native flask code.</p>

<p>We strongly recommend that you set up a <a href="http://www.virtualenv.org/">virtualenv</a> for this project, and you may also want to check out <a href="http://virtualenvwrapper.readthedocs.org/">virtualenvwrapper</a> for convenience. This is to provide your app with a sandboxed environment.</p>

<h5>Getting up and running with Flask</h5>

<p>Lets first install Flask</p>

<p>```bash
pip install Flask</p>

<h1>For viewing and reusing app dependencies</h1>

<p>pip freeze > requirements.txt
```
Set up the following directory structure in your app.</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<p>├── README.md
├── app.py
├── requirements.txt
└── templates</p>

<pre><code>└── index.html
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Modify your app.py code to include the following</p>

<p>```python
from flask import Flask, render_template</p>

<p>app = Flask(<strong>name</strong>)</p>

<p>@app.route("/")</p>

<p>def index():</p>

<pre><code>return render_template('index.html')
</code></pre>

<p>if <strong>name</strong> == "<strong>main</strong>":</p>

<pre><code>app.run()
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>We start by importing Flask and creating a new instance of a flask application. In flask, app.route is used to describe the behavior when users hit particular endpoints in the application. Here when user hits the index route, we render a template called hello world. By default Flask uses the Jinja2 templating language, but you can use any other templating language. In fact, we will not be covering Jinja2 in this blog post. Finally we tell python to call the run method of the app when invoked as a main function.</p>

<p>Let's populate index.html with the following basic HTML boilerplate</p>

<p>```html</p>

<p>&lt;!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head></p>

<pre><code>&lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Flask React Tutorial&lt;/title&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></head>
<body></p>

<pre><code> &lt;div id="mount-point"&gt;
     &lt;p1&gt;Hello world.&lt;/p1&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></body>
</html>
```</p>

<p>Now run the app with</p>

<p><code>bash
python app.py
// * Running on http://127.0.0.0:5000/
// * Restarting with reloader
</code>
By default it runs on port 5000. Navigate to the endpoint and you should see the html page you just created. You are now up and running with Flask!</p>

<h5>Integrate React</h5>

<p>Easiest way to include React would be to just include them from a cdn. Let's update the index.html to include React and and port our existing html to React. index.html will now look like</p>

<p>```html</p>

<p>&lt;!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head></p>

<pre><code>&lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Flask React Tutorial&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;script src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/react/0.13.2/react.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/react/0.13.2/JSXTransformer.js"&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></head>
<body></p>

<pre><code> &lt;div id="mount-point"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></body></p>

<p>  <script type="text/jsx"></p>

<pre><code> /*** @jsx React.DOM */
var FirstComponent = React.createClass({
    render: function() {
        return (&lt;p1&gt;Hello world.&lt;/p1&gt;);
    }
});
React.render(&lt;FirstComponent /&gt;, document.getElementById('mount-point') );
 &lt;/script&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></html>
```</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Let's go over the code. We first include the react and jsx libraries via the script tags and remove the earlier p tags. We set up a jsx script by specifying type="text/jsx". Then we call createClass method of React which creates a React component. React components are reusable units that you can use to compose your UI. The component must have at least the render method, which returns the virtual representation of a native DOM element or another component.
Next we call React.render with the first element and pass it the id of the div element on which we want the result of the render function to be. Run the app again to navigate to the same path to see the app again.</p>

<h5>Data binding with React</h5>

<p>For a more practical example, as well to demonstrate multiple components, let's produce a type along data binding example. You can replace your script tag with the following</p>

<p>```html</p>

<script type="text/jsx">
    /** @jsx React.DOM */
    var Input = React.createClass({
        updateLabel: function(event){
            this.setState({value: event.target.value});
        },
        getInitialState: function(){
            return {
                value: ''
            }
        },
        componentWillMount: function(){
            this.setState({value: this.state.value})
        },
        render: function(){
            return (
                <div className="update-label">
                      <input type="text" placeholder="Enter text" onChange={this.updateLabel}/>
                    <Label value={this.state.value}/>
                </div>
        )
    }
});

var Label = React.createClass({
    render: function(){
        return (
        <div class="my-label">
        <h2>{this.props.value}</h2>
        </div>
        )
    }
});

React.render(<Input/>, document.getElementById('mount-point'));
</script>


<p>```</p>

<p>As before, React.render is called at the very end on a component called Input and it is bound to the element with id mount-point. Inside the Input component a few other lifecycle functions are introduced.</p>

<p>The method getInitialState is called once before the component mounts and  responsible for setting for the initial state of a component.
componentWillMount is called directly before a react component is initially rendered. Inside componentWillMount, we invoke setState.</p>

<p>setState can trigger UI updates from event handlers and server request callbacks. It will always cause a re-render to happen. Once render is called, it returns a div with a input box and a React component called label. We attach the method updateLabel which gets invoked when the text inside the input box changes. It updates this.state.value.</p>

<p>State attributes are mutable within a component and are used to represent the interaction changes changes within a component. On the other hand, props are immutable and used to pass data from a parent component to a child. In this case Label is a child component of Input, and this.state.value for Input is passed to Label, which can access it by this.props.value. Thus Input passes the data entered into the input box to Label and causes it to re-render and display the text.</p>

<p>Fire up the server again and type something into the input box and the content gets updated in the h2 element underneath.</p>

<h5>Why React</h5>

<p>As it turns out, the selling points of React are not super hard to get and clear use cases became obvious.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>React is very efficient in the way it handles DOM updates. It is important however, to isolate that heavy rendering or interactions are the bottlenecks so that you are not optimizing prematurely and likely already have optimized database interactions and network calls.</p></li>
<li><p>SEO management overhead can be less with React compared to Angular/Ember since it can be rendered server side. The benefit comes from not having the overhead of rendering your page server side with something like PhantomJS and serving the HTML.</p></li>
<li><p>Reusable components make the code more reusable and testable, and the short terminology keeps the learning curve managable.</p></li>
<li><p>Since React can be rendered Server Side, you might completely get rid of your server side templating, further reducing the number of tools necessary to run your app.</p></li>
</ol>


<h5>React and Flask</h5>

<p>With their focus on SRP, React and Flask could be dependable and efficient parts of your stack. This is specially handy if you want to leverage the Numpy/Scipy stack for doing data analysis in near realtime and serve up a frontend with heavy user interaction. In a later post, we will look at exploring interactive applications and introduce Socket.io.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scipy 2014: Python as expression to push boundaries in science]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2014/07/13/scipy-2014-python-as-expression-to-push-boundaries-in-science/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-13T20:22:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2014/07/13/scipy-2014-python-as-expression-to-push-boundaries-in-science</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's not everyday that the person sitting next to you interacts with Mars Rovers everyday or is trying to build a data pipeline to handle petabyte-scale genomics data. But that was perhaps the key takeway from my first <a href="https://conference.scipy.org/scipy2014/">Python conference</a>: a large number of people pushing the boundaries in scientific disciplines and using Python as their means of expression.</p>

<p>I have been using Python for a while now, both at work and for hobby projects but until of late have mostly been in the peripheries in contributions to open source projects. When I learned about Scientific Python conference right near to me in Austin, I was immediately interested. If you buy that there is such a thing as language wars, scientific computing has been one of Python's key wins. With libraries such as NumPy, Matplotlib and Pandas (and of course IPython), Python have dominated the Scientific Python landscape alongside R and Julia.</p>

<p>When such a strong ecosystem is matched by a very welcoming community, there is a recipe for a conference worth being at. Well, If you can get past the imposter syndrome of being at a place with the highest density of phds of any place I have ever been at.</p>

<h3>Takeaways</h3>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Python catching up in areas where it lacked</strong>:
Performance, distribution, scalibility and reproducability were some of main themes at the conference. This addresses some of the historic lackings of the language. Sometimes this is via adoption of new tools such as docker for containerizing work enviroments for remote co-working researchers. Dependency on other languages has been one of the major pain points in working with the scientific Python libraries, so it is great to see Conda and HashDist (which I just discovered) to take that head on. Interoperability and scalability are two of the main problems Blaze is solving, and Bokeh and Plotly takes on the problems of publishing and sharing interactive visualizations in Python.</p></li>
<li><p><strong> New tools for my workflow</strong>:
There are many tools which deserve a space here, but I was primarily exited to discover pyspark, yt, plotly, sumatra/vistrails, hashdist and airspeed velocity. Version control and workflow control are familiar terratories for software engineers, but the idea of event control was new to me, something explored in a Birds of a feather discussion.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Birds of a Feather talks are revealing</strong>:
Birds of a feather discussions were sometimes my favorite, where there was candid sharing of painpoints and their solutions from the community members. It was also good to know what were the open problems in various areas are as they often indicate valuable areas to focus on.</p></li>
</ol>


<!-- more -->


<ol>
<li><p><strong>Contributions are needed</strong>:
It was great to see a lot of egoless collaboration during the conference. Maintainers of projects were willing to deprecate their hard work in favor of a better accepted tool in the community. At the same time, lot of the development of very instrumental tools seem to be done by a small group of people, highlighting the need for more collaborators in this space.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Sprints are like speed dating for open source projects</strong>:
SciPy sprints were very different environment from hackathons. With the removal of prize as a factor, what remains is people who enjoy their work and often are highly productive. With the large number of projects available and the acceptance by the core developers, I had the opportunity to work on the charting library Bokeh, serialization library Dill, hack on datasets with yt developers (because random access over a 32 TB file served by apache to generate a graph on Ipython fully client side is seriously impressive) and dig into dockerizing web apps and databases with the reproducable workflow group. All in two days work.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>As someone who is primarily an app developer, this conference was challenging as I have diverged from the path of scientific research a while back. Despite that, I have came away with a strong appreciation for the scientific python community and ecosystem and must thank PayPal for letting me attend the confrence.</p>

<p>To finish, the keynote on the third day by Greg Wilson was quite fantastic and you should check it out if you haven't already:</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/1e26rp6qPbA" allowfullscreen></iframe></div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hack the Trackers]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/12/25/hack-the-trackers-november/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-25T15:49:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/12/25/hack-the-trackers-november</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Online tracking has been a peak topic of debate this year and by the look of things will continue to be. NSA programs, Snowden and the reactions from top tech companies brought in more attention to tracking than ever before. It was hence very timely for Evidon/Ghostery to organize hack the trackers in early November.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.ghostery.com/">Ghostery</a> is a chrome extension that displays trackers on a particular webpage. Not only that, they allow features to block particular trackers and include detailed information about the trackers. The emphasis seems to make web users aware of tracking and let them make the choice.</p>

<p>We built Falcon, which we thought would complement Ghostery's offering quite well. Falcon is a chrome extension where we displayed the overall lost time due to the trackers and which trackers were the most resource intensive. Our hypothesis was that to increase awareness of online tracking, we needed to provide tangible ways in which tracking affects online browsing experience. Ghostery provided us with a data set with a lot of interesting information, among which average load time for trackers was a key indicator. Even with caching, users could lose time which would take to load the trackers, if trackers are loaded synchronously. This could particularly matter for mobile and locations with poor wi-fi as poorly created trackers would slow down the browsing experience.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/falcon.png" width="500" height="900" title="Falcon Demo" alt="Falcon Demo"></p>

<p>Building a chrome extension for a first time was not too complicated as it is very similar to building a web page and chrome is as reliable as platforms get. We ended up being one of the two semi finalists, the other being a cool way to link the trackers with their public figures as a fun way to raise attention to tracking.</p>

<p>This hackathon was particularly a great learning experience. Companies are taking highly innovative routes to glean more information about the users. Cookies have always existed, but two other forms of tracking I learnt was autocomplete fields tracking and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Device_fingerprint">browser fingerprinting</a>. Browser fingerprinting tries to get information from user-agent, the OS, extensions installed and other configurations to bind a particular browser to an user and this can happen completely on the server side. I have only learnt fairly recently about the bidding platforms for display advertisement and it was pretty interesting to see dictionary.com revealing on their console the bids as they happened in real time.</p>

<p>Computer security is a dynamic and fast changing field and this hackathon was an interesting mix of people in different niches of the industry. Tracking will continue to be an issue and it was good to see Ghostery taking the initiative to search for innovations in this space.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
