<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Fitness | Avi Das]]></title>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/categories/fitness/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-11-24T17:28:33-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://avidas.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Avi (Ananya Das)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chicago Marathon 2019 Race Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2019/11/23/chicago-marathon-2019-race-report/"/>
    <updated>2019-11-23T17:12:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2019/11/23/chicago-marathon-2019-race-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>A big step forward and lessons learnt along the way.</em></p>

<p><strong>Race Day</strong></p>

<p>For goal races, I usually wake up before the alarm goes off. October 13th was no different. Despite the 3:30 am wakeup, I slept unusally well considering it was the night before the race. I KT taped my foot carefully, which I had to do throughout the training cycle to defend against feet issues. After the usual overpacking of gear check bag, I joined my Dashing Whippet housemates on the train ride to the starting line.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/marathon_photos/pre_race.jpg" width="350" height="350" title="Pre race" alt="Pre race"></p>

<p>In the race village, I watched the sea of green feet (nike Next %s), and waited till it was time to get to the start line. The race corral was already busy over half hour left before race start. I went through the motions of shedding extra clothing, doing warmups in the cramped environment and holding back the nerves. It was colder than I expected, which wasn’t a bad thing at all. It would stay cool during the whole race, which meant overheating never became an issue.</p>

<p>At the start line, I felt good. No major injuries have cropped up since March, and training went as well as it could. Despite that, I wanted to stay committed to running a smart race. Marathon is too long of a race distance to predict an outcome and I wanted to stay within myself as long as possible.</p>

<p>I saw the 3:15 pacemaker, and realized I was in two minds whether to go with him or not. I decided to trust my training and focus on running my own race.</p>

<p>The race began, and in the beginning mile I stayed attentive to what my body was telling me. The surge of adrenaline wanted me to speed up, but I held back and moved with caution. At mile 1, I heard my name from a friend cheering and immediately felt better. It is so valuable to see familiar faces during a race.</p>

<p>As early as mile 2, my GPS was completely haywire. I had to stop paying attention to the speed that the GPS was showing me and decided to count every 5k interval instead. I knew those times by heart from training.</p>

<p><em>23, 46, 1:09, 1:32, 1:55, 2:18, 2:41, 3:04…</em></p>

<p>I got to 5k within the limit without much issues. Chicago is one of the best marathons, and crowd support is a big part of that. The first half of Chicago is electric, with non stop crowd support, and they showed up strong on an overcast, windy day. It feels as if hundreds of thousands of people are on your side, and you want to run well for their sake.</p>

<p>Then next 5k also went fairly quickly. I have found the miles between 8-12 mentally tough during training and it was definitely no different during race day, injecting some doubt into my race strategy. Every person racing at their limit must battle negative thoughts, there is really no other way.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/marathon_photos/chicago_most_photogenic_mp_1.png" width="350" height="350" title="Chicago 20k" alt="Chicago 20k"></p>

<p>At 15k, I was able to keep a buffer of over a minute. It wasn’t clear to me whether the pace was sustainable the whole course. I wasn’t looking at the watch until a 5k interval, so there wasn’t much to rely on other than how I felt running. I kept repeating the words in my head.</p>

<p><em>Smooth. Calm. Relaxed. Metronomic.</em></p>

<p><em>Stay as calm as a Tibetan Monk.</em></p>

<p><em>Only a couple hours or so and I can go run trails.</em></p>

<p>Around mile 11 or 12 during the race, another runner cut sharply into my path, a near collision. As I looked at him, I went from bewilderment to anger to laughing out loud in the period of a second. “Wherever you are trying to go dude, I hope you get there", I said silently as I shrugged and carried on.</p>

<p>I thought about getting to the start line and getting up to this point. I thought about the Tuesday night tempo workouts, Thursday night speed workouts in East River, Saturday morning long runs, all the work that went in. Even if the race fell apart at some point, there would solace in knowing that I came this far. Maybe I could go on for another 5k.</p>

<p>Once I passed 20k, I was getting more in the zone. There is a lot of beautiful Chicago neighborhoods the race takes you through. There are people carrying signs and blasting music and screaming words of affirmation from the sidelines. I don’t remember any of them specifically though. I remember staying close to the blue line as much as possible, which marked the point to point 26.2 miles on the course.</p>

<p>I crossed 13.1 miles at 1:36:21, well within goal time and feeling well. I was feeling well with the pacing, at the same time the relative effort was feeling harder with each 5k. I was feeling searing pain in my foot, but there wasn’t much I could do. The only possible option was to continue forward.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The plan was to stay ahead of hydration and nutrition, and it got me very well up to 25k and then onto 30k on pace. Around then my stomach started cramping up, meaning I was no longer able to take in more gels. This is the point of the race when the mental game really begins. I was still holding out hope for a late surge, but it would prove to be wishful thinking.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/marathon_photos/chicago_pain_face_mp_1.png" width="350" height="350" title="Chicago 40k" alt="Chicago 40k"></p>

<p>Past 35k, this is where the race got really difficult. Each mile felt like it spun forever and legs felt heavier. This is also the part of the race where the crowd thinned out, so support was few and far between. I felt as though I didn’t have space for either negative or positive thoughts. All of energy and attention was necessary to keep prodding ahead.</p>

<p>In my past four marathons, at the three hour mark of a marathon, I have quite a bit of running left to do. This was noticeably different. There was less than fifteen minutes of running left and it was time to empty the tanks.</p>

<p>As it turned out, the tanks were empty enough already, and maintaining pace was all my legs could manage. At this point, I was running back into the city, and the spectators were really turning up the cheering. I needed all the help here. The last couple miles bought blast of headwinds, the largest hill of the course and a sprint across the final stretch. I looked at the watch, it said 3:13, a PR of almost 26 minutes. Mission accomplished.</p>

<p><strong>Buildup to Chicago</strong></p>

<p>I got in to Chicago Marathon through the lottery early December 2018. Chicago was my second marathon back in 2016, and I had good memories from that year. Late 2018, I was on the road to recovery from lingering Plantar Fasciitis and feeling optimistic. I must have felt too optimistic though, as I hurried back into training only to get sidelined with a metatarsal stress fracture. To add to that, my shoulder  got injured from rock climbing, making it a tough winter to go through. In mid March I was finally able to run/walk again and had to be careful to build back with caution.</p>

<p>In March, Chicago felt very far away. Injuries have plagued me since August, and I haven’t had a personal best race since April 2018. I decided that doing the NYRR 9+1 would be a good way to get back into racing and have more near term races. The first one was early May, Fiesta 5k race in Jersey City. It went well, giving me a boost in confidence.</p>

<p>It won’t last long though as the next one was Brooklyn half, where I went in badly suffering from allergies and after exiting Prospect Park at mile 7, I found it impossible to breathe. Thankfully Lisa, a running friend from Austin, found me and we jogged the rest of the way. It was demoralizing to go through, but every day cannot be a win.</p>

<p>In the following weeks, I was steadily increasing mileage, able to gradually get back to doing workouts again and do more NYRR races: the Italy run, Pride run, sprinkle in some trail runs. The benefit of all these was that I was able to enjoy running again. I was learning how to pace myself in shorter distances. At the same time, I had to be patient. Those were not my goal races.</p>

<p>As temperatures rose during the summer, so did mileage. In July, I got back to doing a 15 mile long run, my longest run of the year. After team championships, it was time to fully dedicate to marathon training. July, August, September combined a total of over 630 miles. This was the first time that I followed a training plan to run a Marathon. It was far from smooth sailing, however.</p>

<p>There were many times I thought the foot injury was back and things were at the edge of falling apart. I would show up at a workout at Central Park and wonder if this would be the day my training cycle would be over. I realized that the only way to get through them was to remind myself that I enjoyed the process, and if this was my last workout, I should enjoy it as much as I can.</p>

<p>During the lead up to the Marathon, I did all I could to sustain the workload. I introduced yoga, daily foam rolling, and core strengthening as ways to support myself as the mileage and training got more demanding. I made sure to never skip warmups and cooldowns around workouts. I prioritized sleep, tried to eat healthy and cut out alcohol completely as the race got closer. I ran my easy days really easy to ensure they promote recovery, running them primarily thinking about form and not the watch.</p>

<p>Then came the 20 milers, which were a steep learning curve after a long break. These runs are key in a Marathon training plan to get ready for when things get really hard during the last 10k of the race. As a tune up race, I ran the 18 miler NYRR run in Central Park. I made some mistakes in that race: started too fast, forgot my gels. I had to check back my pace at mile 7 since the effort was too much but then was able to recover and steadily progress again. Despite feeling spent after that effort, it gave me a lot of confidence executing close to marathon effort for that long.</p>

<p>I had a meeting with coach Forti and discussed race day planning. He suggested running 23 minute 5ks since it mapped well to my time goal. I haven’t tried this before, but I liked the idea of looking at my watch less.</p>

<p>During the two week taper, I significantly reduced mileage to let the body heal. More than a time goal, showing up at starting line healthy would be a great win and I wanted that win.</p>

<p>I stayed with Dashing Whippets teammates in Chicago, which helped with pre race nerves, since the whole group was going through it. The day before the race, we did a shakeout run with the Heartbreak Hill Running Company in Chicago.</p>

<p><strong>Post Race</strong></p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/marathon_photos/chicago_end.jpg" width="350" height="350" title="Post Race" alt="Post Race"></p>

<p>It felt really good after the race. You can hypothesize about a Marathon goal, but it is just a theory until it happens in a race. It vindicated that a lot of things were done right during this training cycle, and revealed areas of improvement necessary to run a stronger Marathon. Marathon is a complex puzzle piece, and all individual components need attention and care to come together on race day.</p>

<p>Where does this leave me? I am deeply grateful for this race, having converted a lot of work that happened during the last two years and not pick up a new injury. It’s a good place to be, but I do feel that progress from here is going to be significantly harder. A potential BQ is still very, very far away. I have decided to not worry about that too much though, rather try to get better at short distance running and do some trail running.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jersey Half Marathon 2018: Race Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2018/05/09/jersey-half-marathon-2018-race-report/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-09T10:21:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2018/05/09/jersey-half-marathon-2018-race-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>"Gatoradeee!! Water!" The sudden enthusiastic cheer after a period of silence was hard to miss. Looking up, I saw the 10k marker. I looked at my watch and I was about to PR a 10k. Except that I was not running a 10k. I was running a half Marathon and with more than half of the race still ahead of me, this was bad news.</p>

<p>Post NYC marathon last November, I was happy to have run my goal race in a good time. I knew I was hitting my upper limits with the Marathon, and without focus on shorter distances, I would not get faster. I focused religiously on the Tuesday tempo and Thursday speed workouts with the Dashing Whippets central park group. It was inspiring to see the people training for Boston Marathon putting in incredible work during some difficult months.</p>

<p>This season’s training posed many challenges, primarily freezing temperature, snowstorms, breakups. Every time I stepped out the door and breathed in the icy air into my lunges, everything inside me wanted to get back inside and wrap myself in a blanket.  But the workouts had a way of enforcing discipline into my life. For Saturdays, I made the commitment to keep showing up and sometimes challenge myself by going with a slightly faster group.</p>

<p>The group kept me going. If everyone else have no problems showing up and putting in the work in dark and cold, I have no excuses not to. When I was in the pain cave during the Jersey Half, that was what going though my head. I am in the deep end, but I owed my 600 mile training cycle a good performance and take responsibility for strategic mistakes early in the race.</p>

<p>As I realized my mess up during the Jersey half, I realized I needed a baseline pace or I would fade. My inner voice said don’t fade, every second counts. So I found couple runners putting down 7:15 miles and making it look like cakewalk. Later I learnt that they were running the marathon. Talking to them helped me get some boost. After that, I found another pace group, and hung with them all the way to the end.</p>

<p>The value of this race as a developing runner is that it answers some lingering questions. How fast am I? Am I capable of taking my progress in training and convert it on race day? Am I training with the right group of people or just tagging along with faster runners for dear life. That’s what this half will mean for me, that I have improved this training cycle and while my strategy and mental game needs work, I can enjoy the following week knowing I made progress. Progress where I used to think there is no way I can hold a 7:09 pace for 13 miles but there is now data to prove otherwise.</p>

<p>So that was the Jersey Half. I am very happy with the result having converted a 10 minute PR. However, I would like to get there next time more gracefully and not feel totally wrecked at the end.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NYC Marathon 2017: Training and Race Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2017/11/07/nyc-marathon-2017-race-report/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-07T09:06:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2017/11/07/nyc-marathon-2017-race-report</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I ran the NYC marathon this Sunday. On my fourth marathon, I was going for 3:45, came off with a 3:38, personal best by 4 minutes. More than the time, a vanity metric, I was happier about the race execution, doing negative splits, avoiding cramps and bonks/hitting the wall. NYC marathon is a technical and challenging course, but I found it could reward patience and training. It was also an emotional roller coaster for me, NYC being a focal point during majority of my time in the US.</p>

<p><strong>Training</strong></p>

<p>Big part of my marathon was made during the months prior. I have ran marathons before, most recently in Feburary in Austin, so I know my body is capable of handling trials of the 26.2. But I was carrying over my adductor injury from March, and since moving to NYC, its been a slow ramp back up on the miles. Joining the Dashing Whippets in NYC was a great decision, as all my running progress can be attributed to training with groups in Austin, Austin Runner's Club and Austin Runner's Meetup. Post June, I had to patiently wait for my speed/endurance to catch up as I stopped running since March. Whippets are a great group, as they are both very competitive and large enough where runners of different paces can have others to run with.</p>

<p>Once summer turned into fall, I was beginning to get the mileage adaptation back up. Besides the Saturday long runs, I worked on Harlem hill repeats on Sundays and speed work with the Whippets on Thursdays. Putting those fast and hilly miles were instrumental to getting myself back into marathon shape. Alongside with Tuesday workout with the whippets, I was able to get my weekly mileage up to 55 early October, more than I'd ever done. However, at this point I had to cut back since the workload was triggering overuse injuries in calves and ankles.</p>

<p>This is what my peak weak mileage looked like</p>

<p>Saturday: 20m long run (Whippets)<br>
Sunday: 8-9m Harlem Hill repeats<br>
Monday: Rest<br>
Tuesday: 12m (Central park Whippets)<br>
Wednesday: 5m easy<br>
Thursday: 10-12m (Speed work on East Side with Whippets)<br>
Friday: Rest<br></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>Nutrition</strong></p>

<p>NYC marathon has been my goal race, and I took nutrition and hydration leading to the race very seriously. Prior to race day, this involved hydrating well, drinking about 1.5 gallon of water a day. It also involved giving up alcohol for a month before the race. I remembered cramps from salt depletion in the Austin marathon, and I added salt to my food leading to race and carried salted water with me on race day. I carb loaded leading to days prior to the race except before race day when I stuck to really simple food heavier in carbs, potatoes, sweat potatoes, eggs. On race morning, I got coffee and simple carbs such as oats, apple and a bagel/banana on the route. During the race, I used 4 Cliff Gels, one every 5 miles, an approach which worked well for me in the Austin Marathon. On the race course, I alternated between water and gatorade every other mile. This helped me avoid cramps and hitting the wall during the race.</p>

<p><strong>Getting to start line</strong></p>

<p>NYC marathon is tough logistics wise, so I wanted to reduce chance of things going wrong as much as possible.  Race day is stressful, and I wanted to limit variability. Spending the night on Wall Street gave me an extra hour of sleep and less subway stress en route to the ferry. Meeting up with friends I have been training with was also good to calm down race day nerves. The ferry ride set a tone as I was feeling excited and giddy with Statue of Liberty looming large in the mist. Waiting for the buses post ferry was more of a slog, with standing long being the last thing I wanted before the marathon. Off the bus, and post Porter Potty visits, I heard the announcement of my Corral being closed in 5 minutes. 5 minutes! I ran frantically to look and find my corral. Eventually I managed to get in just in time for my wave. That left half an hour of waiting for the race.</p>

<p>I dressed warm heading to Staten Island, and this was the time to get rid of the baggage and get some warmup in my system. I love talking to runners before races. In a race like the NYC Marathon, everyone I talked to had a super interesting story.</p>

<p><strong>The race</strong></p>

<p><strong>Staten Island</strong></p>

<p>For the first time, I decided to run a marathon without a pacer, phone or watch. I put trust in that my experience of running 3 marathons and training would be enough to run by what Marathon effort should feel like. My goal was to be conservative as long as possible as a course like NYC deserves respect and a cautious approach.</p>

<p>After the short opening ceremony, we finally took off. It immediately started drizzling rain, not ideal but far from worst conditions. My spirits were pretty high, despite everything, I was running the NYC Marathon! As we ran up the Verrazano Bridge, I wished for a clearer day as the iconic view of Manhattan on top of the Verrazano was blurry in the fog. I brought my focus back to the road and the blue line markers on the road, which mark the point to point 26.2 mile during the race.</p>

<p><strong>Brooklyn</strong></p>

<p>Downhill from the Verrazano, it was steep decline but not the time to speed. I checked my pace, letting most runners pass me by. We were gradually moving down the bridge towards Brooklyn, which could only mean one thing. Crowd support!</p>

<p>And what a crowd it was! Brooklyn was my favorite part of the race. They brought music, diversity, energy and smiles. Bay ridge leading to Park Slope, Flatbush and then running through Williamsburg was an absolute riot in the best way possible. There were times when if I spread out my hands I could reach spectators on both sides. Not a problem with such a well behaved and well wishing crowd. There were bands and choirs and some great signs: "You can overcome the path once you become the path itself".</p>

<p>NYC Marthon is a race of two halves. Most of the first half is in Brooklyn and is also some of the easier parts of the course. My goal here was to run slightly under Marathon effort, and making sure to fuel/get water along the way.</p>

<p><strong>Queens</strong></p>

<p>Finally we were at the halfway point in the race, up top the Pulaski bridge. We heard the announcement that Shalane Flannagan just won the women's race and groups of people erupted into cheers. This set a great tone leading into Queens.</p>

<p>Queens does not get a lot of mileage but it is the lead up the most talked about part of the course, the infamous climb up the Queensboro bridge at mile 15.</p>

<p>This was a key part of the race for me. For the second half of the course, I wanted to start pushing, starting with uphills. Hence Queensboro was the acid test for how my marathon would shape up. While the ride up Queensboro was hard, I was passing people all the way which gave me a lot of confidence.</p>

<p><strong>Manhattan to Bronx</strong></p>

<p>As we ran down Queensboro, a low hum grew louder and finally erupted into cheers as we descended down Queensboro to reach Manhattan. The crowd here is boisterous and makes for a landmark moment of running this race.</p>

<p>In Manhattan, going up 1st avenue, my priority was to still run at a fairly conservative pace as there was still 10+ miles left. Getting rid of my waistbelt at mile 16 was helpful as I got rid of some weight. The latter part of 1st avenue is surprisingly hard psycologically, as crowd support fell further into the course. This was also the part of the race where goals and training for the race starts to become important.</p>

<p>Crossing the Willis bridge, we got to Bronx. I have ran this part of the course, and I was looking forward to the Whippets cheering section, which comes right at the edge of Bronx, at mile 21 as I moved my way back into Manhattan. It was at this point too that I was starting to realize not only I could break 3:45 but a PR (personal record) was possible, which brought a fresh wave of motivation.</p>

<p><strong>Back to Manhattan towards central park</strong></p>

<p>Back into Manhattan, going across fifth avenue, this is where I started to increase to full effort, knowing that with each step, the course was getting more and more into familiar terratory. Despite that, mile 23 was likely the most challenging of the whole race, a steady incline up 5th avenue on tired legs. But this also where the training mattered the most.</p>

<p>Once we entered Central park on 91st street, this was the home stretch. This is where I was really going for it, fixing my attention on one runner, catching up to them and repeating. I have ran central park enough to know the inclines and declines and with every step, it was getting closer to finish line. We were on mile 26 and at this point we left the park, run adjacent to it and finally come back. The last 400 yards were memorable, running through a painful haze but moving closer to that immaculate finish line and eventually reaching it. I knew I had PRed, I did not know by how much yet.</p>

<p><strong>Post Race thoughts</strong></p>

<p>Broadcasting to everyone how to track me on race day was motivating for me as I knew friends and family in NYC, Austin and Bangladesh would be watching. Ultimately, NYC being my goal race, I wanted to give everything I was capable of. 2017 NYC marathon was a race in which I was able to apply some of the race advice and strategies and this was the first time I'd ever hit negative splits in a race. It was really an unforgettable race, running with 50,000+ people and going through all the iconic NYC sights.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10 things I learnt going from 10k to a Marathon in 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2016/02/09/10-things-i-learnt-going-from-10k-to-a-marathon-in-2015/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-09T23:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2016/02/09/10-things-i-learnt-going-from-10k-to-a-marathon-in-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If I were to think about running a 26.2 mile race at the start of 2015, the overwhelming feeling would be one of fear. I have only ever ran a 10k before and just signed up for the Austin 2015 half Marathon, my first ever half. The prospect of running twice the distance still seemed far away though. Flash forward to October 18th 2015, I finished my first Marathon with a 3:49:00 time. As I look back on this year, I wanted to put together some of my realizations during the whole process. </p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Running is a privilege</strong>:
Living somewhere where I can run safely, have trails to run on, be in good health to run are all privileges to be thankful for. Growing up in the developing world meant that it was hard pressed to find opportunities to be involved in outdoor activites. Having the time and space to exercise is a luxury that needed to be earned. I never ran in high school, and by the time I graduated college I could not run longer than 5k. Having the time to run, being in US where running is very much part of the culture has been a huge contributor to my running progress.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Joining a running group is one of the best decisions you can make as a beginning runner</strong>:
Training with people better than you to improve is not unique to running. Start of 2015, I had no plans of running a marathon. In April, I joined the Austin Runners Meetup (ARM). In training long runs with ARM, I was able to build up the endurance for longer runs which made the progression to a Marathon much easier mentally. Training with other runners can definitely help you maintain the habit of running as well as improve your form and performance. Moreover, I found a new community of great people which has been very rewarding.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Tying running with other activities you enjoy can make running much more consistent</strong>:
In Charles Duhigg's <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Power-Habit-What-Business/dp/081298160X">Power of Habit</a>, he talks about the cue-action-reward pattern that most habits follow. Being aware of that pattern can help in building running as a habit. When run's are followed by a delicious breakfast, you have something to look forward to. Trance music and podcasts help me maintain the flow during running. Travel is one of my favorite things and going to a new city for a race is something I eagerly look forward to.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Running is a blissful release from life's distractions</strong>:</p>

<blockquote><p>“All I do is keep on running in my own cozy, homemade void, my own nostalgic silence. And this is a pretty wonderful thing.” 
― Haruki Murakami, What I Talk About When I Talk About Running```</p></blockquote>

<p> Distractions are part and parcel of our lives as more form factors emerge competing for our limited attention span. Often, this results in us not being aware of the passage of time. Running has been a great antidote to that problem for me. When running is effortful, you have to concentrate on the activity at hand and your entire focus is on the present moment. Long runs offer the prospect of seeing places and neighborhoods that you would not frequent otherwise. A slight breeze on a scorching summer's day has never been more enjoyable.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Once running is a habit, a chore becomes a craving</strong>:
When you start out running, it can be something you dread on your calendar. There is really no way to get past this without sustained practice, lowering the cognitive load with group associations and reward mechanisms. If you continue though, you realize at one point that you start craving the runs. Don't get me wrong, it still requires a lot of mental effort to get up at 5:30am for that 20 mile run you need to do for Marathon training. But something about the combination of endorphins, habits built during running and seeing your friends out there on the trail can change running into something that you look forward to.</p></li>
</ol>


<!-- more -->


<ol>
<li><p><strong>You only compete against your past self</strong>:
This can vary a lot based on personality, but being slower than a lot of other runners has never really bothered me that much. As long as I beat my previous PR by two seconds, I would be happy. Running as an activity has been such a positive change for my life that the gratification from being faster than others has not been necessary at all. Lot of people starting out running also worry about their pace. However, beginner runners should actually run slower than the pace they think they can run at to avoid injury and build up distance and time.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Respect your body's adjustment mechanisms</strong>:
One of my foremost running philosophies is to avoid injury. Running is a full body exercise. Your heart, muscles, ligaments and joints all need adjust to the increased level of physical activity. In the beginning, you run out of breath since your heart is simply not used to pumping out the necessary amount of oxygen to the muscles. However, it can adjust remarkably fast, and you may be tempted to run faster than you should. Getting past muscle cramps is often the next step. Your joints likely will be the last to adjust though, and care should be taken to not run too fast too soon to avoid injury.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Hard things are often the most rewarding</strong>:
If a Marathon was easy, the feeling of achievement would be less profound. You will be in pain after finishing a Marathon. However, if there is any time when pain feels besides the point, this is it. Finishing a Marathon feels good in a way that is hard to find a parallel in our day to day life. Rather you feel as accomplished as a battle commander from the middle ages after winning a long and arduous war.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>It will affect you positively in ways you may not expect</strong>:
When I talk to people about running, I consistently discover new and positive impacts running has had on their lives. For some people if is therapeutic and a great way to cope against troubles in life. It stands out as one of the activities that can have an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle">80/20 impact</a> on your life, since the improvement in concentration and physical ability that you gain from running regularly can help in most other areas of life.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>It gives you the satisfaction of reaching your goals and finishing</strong>:
There are lot of things in life that can drag on, get pushed on and not have a clear resolution. Life is rarely black or white. Running is often a refreshing break from all that. Once you finish a race, it is done and over with, offering the joy of finishing something. Moreover, looking forward and planning for the race can become an exciting activity, as you look to vindicate your hard hours of training.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Running is ultimately a very solitary activity. It does not matter if you train with a group, you are going to be on your own for long periods of time. This makes everyone's running journey very personaI. If you are starting out running in 2016 or have certain training goals, I wish you all the best. If you have already been running races, I hope there was still something useful in this post for you. Either way, feel free to reach out or leave a note. I would love to hear from you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
