<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Hackathon | Avi Das]]></title>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/categories/hackathon/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-06-19T20:32:43-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://avidas.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Avi (Ananya Das)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Connected car: Meticulous.io @Angelhack]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2014/01/07/connected-car-at-angelhack/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-07T23:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2014/01/07/connected-car-at-angelhack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Angelhack looks for startups to come out of hackathons rather than just weekend hacks. As a result, it tends to get very product driven as teams compete for the Angelpad recognition. The theme this year was Apphack, and mobile apps were the key focus. Not really a surprise, as more and more startups build mobile first.</p>

<p>We worked on the verizon telematics data. <a href="http://www.verizontelematics.com/">Verizon telematics</a> is something I did not know about before. Car companies have been working with Verizon to install a device in the cars that could send data about speed, location, rpm, condition of the car in terms of last time since gas, particular model of car, wear and tear to the cloud. I expect Verizon is able to collect a lot more than the columns we saw. Needless to say, this would be a very powerful dataset and it is surprising that there aren't more going on in this space.</p>

<p><a href="http://ipython.org/">iPython</a> and <a href="http://pandas.pydata.org/">Pandas</a> are built for analyzing and visualizing tabular data like this. Questions such as which brand of car gave the best milage per gallon, which brand was driven more on the highway vs which was more popular on the city roads were fairly easy to answer. It was not clear if the data given to us was indeed an uniform sample, but results were interesting. However, they are hardly hackathon worthy ideas.</p>

<p>Needed an idea. One set of data had trip ids tied to driver ids, the other set had per trip latitudes and longitudes. Aggregating them somehow would be interesting. Geographical history of most visited places can be found since trips could be tied to drivers. Historical driving records could be obtained from individual trips and the overall history of the driver measured. Global driving records could be obtained so that the best driver's can be found.</p>

<p>Once noting those features, the next step was to think how this would make sense as a product. Context sensitive software is hugely in demand and this is a great dataset for revealing patterns of drivers. Buisnesses aware of customers frequenting particular location can push deals and coupons to those individuals to drive buisness. Timeliness of visit can be used to fine tune the deals even more, e.g. lunch deals would make sense around the Grand Central area in NYC to a busy professional. The brand of car can be used to push vehicle specific ads. This would also be a treasure trove of information for car insurance companies figuring out insurance rates. Finally, it is quite possible that driving patterns can be used to trigger alert that may detect an accident ahead of time.</p>

<p>Its hard to argue that driving patterns are valuable data. However, as with any user specific information used for personalization experiences curated by businesses, privacy would be a big concern. It was not entirely clear who would own the data, the driver, the provider, or else. It should be made very clear to the driver of the nature of the tracking going on and how the data may be used. Since data like this could easily be used by a malicious third party to monitor you in real time when you are driving, there is inherent danger in it being available without the driver being informed. Tracking is an issue users of any clowd aware system needs to be aware of.</p>

<p>We did win the Verizon prize for the hackathon, and it was nice having our idea at the eleventh hour being well accepted. Angelhack put on a good show, and I must mention the apps "Make it Rain" (literally, on the phone screen) and "Kanye"(alerts if you are nearby Kanye West) for the hilarity during the presentation!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hack the Trackers]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/12/25/hack-the-trackers-november/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-25T15:49:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/12/25/hack-the-trackers-november</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Online tracking has been a peak topic of debate this year and by the look of things will continue to be. NSA programs, Snowden and the reactions from top tech companies brought in more attention to tracking than ever before. It was hence very timely for Evidon/Ghostery to organize hack the trackers in early November.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.ghostery.com/">Ghostery</a> is a chrome extension that displays trackers on a particular webpage. Not only that, they allow features to block particular trackers and include detailed information about the trackers. The emphasis seems to make web users aware of tracking and let them make the choice.</p>

<p>We built Falcon, which we thought would complement Ghostery's offering quite well. Falcon is a chrome extension where we displayed the overall lost time due to the trackers and which trackers were the most resource intensive. Our hypothesis was that to increase awareness of online tracking, we needed to provide tangible ways in which tracking affects online browsing experience. Ghostery provided us with a data set with a lot of interesting information, among which average load time for trackers was a key indicator. Even with caching, users could lose time which would take to load the trackers, if trackers are loaded synchronously. This could particularly matter for mobile and locations with poor wi-fi as poorly created trackers would slow down the browsing experience.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/falcon.png" width="500" height="900" title="Falcon Demo" alt="Falcon Demo"></p>

<p>Building a chrome extension for a first time was not too complicated as it is very similar to building a web page and chrome is as reliable as platforms get. We ended up being one of the two semi finalists, the other being a cool way to link the trackers with their public figures as a fun way to raise attention to tracking.</p>

<p>This hackathon was particularly a great learning experience. Companies are taking highly innovative routes to glean more information about the users. Cookies have always existed, but two other forms of tracking I learnt was autocomplete fields tracking and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Device_fingerprint">browser fingerprinting</a>. Browser fingerprinting tries to get information from user-agent, the OS, extensions installed and other configurations to bind a particular browser to an user and this can happen completely on the server side. I have only learnt fairly recently about the bidding platforms for display advertisement and it was pretty interesting to see dictionary.com revealing on their console the bids as they happened in real time.</p>

<p>Computer security is a dynamic and fast changing field and this hackathon was an interesting mix of people in different niches of the industry. Tracking will continue to be an issue and it was good to see Ghostery taking the initiative to search for innovations in this space.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[VIPHackathon: Know Your Reps]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/08/04/viphackathon-know-your-reps/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-04T09:58:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/08/04/viphackathon-know-your-reps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/Obama_eagle.jpg" width="350" height="350" title="Obama eagle" alt="Obama eagle"></p>

<p>How many people know their representatives for council/state/congress? How many local issues gets routed to the most relevant elected official? How do you know the status of the most relevant issues raised?</p>

<p>To solve some of these issues, we worked on the "Know your representatives" app during the Voting Information Project hackathon on 8/3/2013 to introduce elected officials to the public. It is a Windows phone app geared to increase accountability of elected officials which in turn will promote voter engagement.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Users can view and contact their official and raise their issues to the respective elected official and raise the most significant issues.</p></li>
<li><p>Official can respond to uses and resolve the issues and update the status on the app.</p></li>
<li><p>Users can add their support to prioritize the high priority items by raising their support using the voting button.</p></li>
</ol>


<!-- more -->


<p> The app was built with Windows Azure as Backend, Twilio is used for sms notification when officials respond to issues. Azavea is used to bring the elected officals information using the Geo Location.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/VIPhack.jpg" width="350" height="350" title="VIP awards" alt="VIP awards"></p>

<p> We ended up winning Microsoft's award for the hackathon! Sadly they only had two phones for the three developers.</p>

<p> Verdict: Twilio's API is super cool, and I definitely intend on building more with it. Never built anything on the Windows Phone platform, but I must say in terms of responsiveness, Visual Studio betters eclipse in many ways. Sync Fusion is a great library for app resources, and a similar product for android would be a godsend. VIP did did a good job showing that many voting problems exist despite US being such a prominent democracy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DevsNearMe : July 26-27 Big Data Hackathon]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/07/28/devsnearme-july-26-27-big-data-hackathon/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T12:54:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/07/28/devsnearme-july-26-27-big-data-hackathon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/24686054 " width="595" height="446" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen></iframe> </p>

<p>Built and won the first prize at the big data hackathon at Alley NYC on July 26-27. The goal is to discover how many people are at a venue at a particular point in time and this app will try to do that for hackers, categorized by skills.</p>

<p>With more and more realtime data being available for the public, identifying knowledge clusters at the right point in time becomes really valuable. DevsNearMe is an Android app that attempts to combine data from popular realtime sharing websites such as FourSquare, Twitter, Facebook, Instagram and MeetUp. It will attempts to predict users at a particular location by taking into account absolute numbers, and weighed prediction based on local context based information and learnt knowledge from past user behavior.</p>

<p>This could be highly useful for knowledge sharing, recruiting and demographic analysis. Prototype code is at https://github.com/DevsNearMe .</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Angelhacking at Dumbo]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/06/08/angelhacking-at-dumbo/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-08T16:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/06/08/angelhacking-at-dumbo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>"This is not your ordinary hackathon. This is the big leagues". Such was the claim of Angelhack this past weekend, and two weeks after participating in my first ever serious hackathon, I found myself at another one. There really is something about the mix of meeting cool people, hacking unfamiliar platforms and testing your coding chops in a small amount of time that can be quite addicting.</p>

<p>Shakere, the product I worked on, is an iPhone app for finding people based on skills or interests in social gatherings. Yes, your umpteenth social product, guilty as charged. The space for social discovery really is a heavily contested one, which made me hesitant at first since variants of the idea has been tried by many. I joined however, after realizing that the team would work well together (we actually had a UX designer in the team. Yay!) and this was my chance to experience iOS development, even though I would be developing the backend.</p>

<p>I worked on rolling a RESTful API (https://github.com/shakere/backend), working on the LAMP stack. Though I have not worked too much on LAMP backends before, I must admit that the stack is well suited for rapid prototyping. PHP in particular was a pleasant surprise to work with, in parts because of working with Perl for most of last year. I have had a little stint with Rails, and while Rails seems far more powerful, PHP is more explicit with less magic going on behind the scenes which makes it easier for starters to tinker. However, I did find myself handling quite a few inc files soon and was grepping to find which function was defined where. If I am working on a larger scale PHP project, it would definitely be worth looking into frameworks/best practices for PHP code organization.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img class="left" src="/images/Shakere_Profile.jpg" width="300" height="800" title="Shakere Profile" alt="Shakere Profile"></p>

<p>We got a neat version working well in time for the demo. The app being frontend heavy, I was done with a bit of time in hand, making it a more pleasant hackathon than the last one. Yet during presentation, we did run into the pitfall of not having tested our demo machines to the projector, and this is really a must if you want to avoid delays during your demos.</p>

<p>The ideas were definitely interesting to look at since the hackathon was not restricted to any particular domain. Some were targeting specifically Microsoft, Paypal or Amazon platforms, who were present at the event and provided prizes for the best app using their APIs. It was specifically interesting when domain experts (such as a scientist in a Columbia lab) came to the hackathon trying to device a service for their community. Field experts can have a certain deep understanding of a space and their demos were a good reflection of that.</p>

<p>We did not win unfortunately but judging did seem fair. The ideas winning were generally the apps which were the most mature or demonstrated a clear need base for their ideas. I particularly enjoyed prepared.ly and their combining the job skill-set with learning tools such as Udacity or CodeAcademy. With some personal analytics and initiatives to pick up the skills fast enough, this service can be very useful for coding job seekers.</p>

<p>For the next such event, I would definitely focus more on rolling out more features faster. We were perhaps guilty of actually going around and getting real user data to populate our databases. I would imagine for pre-shipping products you would want this, and MVPs these days certainly value user early user feedback. Hackathons have different needs from production apps though, and rapid feature deployment wins over iterating and getting existing features perfect. You live and you learn.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
