<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Reading, | Avi Das]]></title>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/categories/reading-/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-05-09T16:30:14-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://avidas.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Avi (Ananya Das)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Books I read in 2018]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2018/12/24/books-i-read-in-2018/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-24T14:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2018/12/24/books-i-read-in-2018</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>General/Personal Development</h3>

<ol>
<li><strong>The art of living (Thich nhat hanh)</strong>: This is the best Thich nhat hanh I've read, composing his philosophy on living an examined life into day to day practices.</li>
<li><strong>Thinking in systems, a primer (Donella Meadows)</strong>: Really, really smart author, systems thinking should be a required course in college.</li>
<li><strong>Ain’t I a Woman: Black Women and Feminism (Bell Hooks)</strong>: Challenges a lot of assumptions, covering black woman's involvement with race identity and feminism.</li>
<li><strong>When: The Scientific Secrets of Perfect Timing (Daniel Pink)</strong>: Dan Pink's books are similar to Malcolm Gladwell's, distilling behavioral psychology research into easy reads.</li>
<li><strong>The Essential Rumi (Jalal Al-Din Rumi)</strong>: Lately I have started admiring how much Poetry can accomplish with so few words. There is something very calming about reading Rumi.</li>
<li><strong>Sex at dawn (Christopher Ryan‎, Cacilda Jethá)</strong>: An incendiary/challenging investigation into human/primate sexuality, sweeping across history to construct the narrative, much like Sapiens by Yuval Noah Harari.</li>
<li><strong>Deep work (Cal Newport)</strong>: So good, anyone doing knowledge/creative work would be benefited by this classic.</li>
<li><strong>The life changing Manga of Tidying Up (Marie Kondo)</strong>: I have been leaning towards minimalism, and Marie Kondo offers very actionable steps to cleaning up, and why doing this is related to the life we want to have.</li>
<li><strong>Flow: The Psychology of Optimal Experience (Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi)</strong>: There is strong evidence at this point that time spent in flow state, (an state of effortless concentration on a single task), can be correlated to contentment/happiness. I really liked the first part of the book but thought it could be much shorter.</li>
<li><strong>Daring Greatly: How the Courage to Be Vulnerable Transforms the Way We Live, Love, Parent, and Lead (Brene Brown)</strong></li>
<li><strong>So good they can’t ignore you (Cal Newport)</strong>: Much like deep work, essential reading for those looking to improve their craft.</li>
<li><strong>How to change your mind (Michael Pollan)</strong>: Eye-opening, challenging look at the resurgence of Psychedelics in mental health research.</li>
<li><strong>A life in parts (Bryan Cranston)</strong></li>
</ol>


<!-- more -->


<h3>Tech</h3>

<ol>
<li><strong>Radical Candor (Kim Scott)</strong></li>
<li><strong>The Phoenix Project: A Novel about IT, DevOps, and Helping Your Business Win (Gene Kim)</strong> A curiously engaging fiction on DevOps and executive level politics in a large tech company.</li>
<li><strong>Designing data intensive applications (Martin Kleppmann)</strong>: One I will be re-reading many times.</li>
<li><strong>The master algorithm (Pedro Domingos)</strong>: An inspiring call to action and possibility of general artificial intelligence.</li>
<li><strong>The manager’s path (Camille Fournier)</strong></li>
<li><strong>The Passionate Programmer: Creating a Remarkable Career in Software Development (Chad Fowler)</strong></li>
</ol>


<h3>Running</h3>

<ol>
<li><strong>Running Rewired: Reinvent Your Run for Stability, Strength, and Speed (Jay Dicharry)</strong></li>
<li><strong>Endure: Mind, Body, and the Curiously Elastic Limits of Human Performance (Alex Hutchinson)</strong></li>
<li><strong>North (Scott Jurek)</strong>: Loved how personal this story was both for Jurek and his wife Jenny, alternating their narratives</li>
<li><strong>Again to Carthage (John L Parker)</strong>: Amazing in certain parts, especially near the end where Cassidy runs Olympic trials, but too long and dragging for most of it.</li>
<li><strong>Running with the mind of meditation (Sakyong Mipham)</strong>: What does a lifelong meditator who also ran the Boston marathon has to say about the sport?</li>
</ol>


<p><em>In no particular order, mostly read while being on the NYC subway!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
