<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Software | Avi Das]]></title>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/categories/software/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-02-17T17:34:38-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://avidas.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Avi (Ananya Das)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scipy 2014: Python as expression to push boundaries in science]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2014/07/13/scipy-2014-python-as-expression-to-push-boundaries-in-science/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-13T20:22:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2014/07/13/scipy-2014-python-as-expression-to-push-boundaries-in-science</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's not everyday that the person sitting next to you interacts with Mars Rovers everyday or is trying to build a data pipeline to handle petabyte-scale genomics data. But that was perhaps the key takeway from my first <a href="https://conference.scipy.org/scipy2014/">Python conference</a>: a large number of people pushing the boundaries in scientific disciplines and using Python as their means of expression.</p>

<p>I have been using Python for a while now, both at work and for hobby projects but until of late have mostly been in the peripheries in contributions to open source projects. When I learned about Scientific Python conference right near to me in Austin, I was immediately interested. If you buy that there is such a thing as language wars, scientific computing has been one of Python's key wins. With libraries such as NumPy, Matplotlib and Pandas (and of course IPython), Python have dominated the Scientific Python landscape alongside R and Julia.</p>

<p>When such a strong ecosystem is matched by a very welcoming community, there is a recipe for a conference worth being at. Well, If you can get past the imposter syndrome of being at a place with the highest density of phds of any place I have ever been at.</p>

<h3>Takeaways</h3>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Python catching up in areas where it lacked</strong>:
Performance, distribution, scalibility and reproducability were some of main themes at the conference. This addresses some of the historic lackings of the language. Sometimes this is via adoption of new tools such as docker for containerizing work enviroments for remote co-working researchers. Dependency on other languages has been one of the major pain points in working with the scientific Python libraries, so it is great to see Conda and HashDist (which I just discovered) to take that head on. Interoperability and scalability are two of the main problems Blaze is solving, and Bokeh and Plotly takes on the problems of publishing and sharing interactive visualizations in Python.</p></li>
<li><p><strong> New tools for my workflow</strong>:
There are many tools which deserve a space here, but I was primarily exited to discover pyspark, yt, plotly, sumatra/vistrails, hashdist and airspeed velocity. Version control and workflow control are familiar terratories for software engineers, but the idea of event control was new to me, something explored in a Birds of a feather discussion.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Birds of a Feather talks are revealing</strong>:
Birds of a feather discussions were sometimes my favorite, where there was candid sharing of painpoints and their solutions from the community members. It was also good to know what were the open problems in various areas are as they often indicate valuable areas to focus on.</p></li>
</ol>


<!-- more -->


<ol>
<li><p><strong>Contributions are needed</strong>:
It was great to see a lot of egoless collaboration during the conference. Maintainers of projects were willing to deprecate their hard work in favor of a better accepted tool in the community. At the same time, lot of the development of very instrumental tools seem to be done by a small group of people, highlighting the need for more collaborators in this space.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Sprints are like speed dating for open source projects</strong>:
SciPy sprints were very different environment from hackathons. With the removal of prize as a factor, what remains is people who enjoy their work and often are highly productive. With the large number of projects available and the acceptance by the core developers, I had the opportunity to work on the charting library Bokeh, serialization library Dill, hack on datasets with yt developers (because random access over a 32 TB file served by apache to generate a graph on Ipython fully client side is seriously impressive) and dig into dockerizing web apps and databases with the reproducable workflow group. All in two days work.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>As someone who is primarily an app developer, this conference was challenging as I have diverged from the path of scientific research a while back. Despite that, I have came away with a strong appreciation for the scientific python community and ecosystem and must thank PayPal for letting me attend the confrence.</p>

<p>To finish, the keynote on the third day by Greg Wilson was quite fantastic and you should check it out if you haven't already:</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/1e26rp6qPbA" allowfullscreen></iframe></div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Best Chrome Productivity Extensions]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2014/06/01/best-chrome-productivity-extensions/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-01T16:40:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2014/06/01/best-chrome-productivity-extensions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How much time during the day do you spend on an internet browser? As a software engineer, my answer is a scary amount of time. Something I have personally struggled with is avoiding distracting sites on the internet. There is too much good content on the internet that dries up my rather finite amount of attention.</p>

<p>Chrome has been my weapon of choice for browsing the web for a while now. Intuitive, clean and fast, Chrome's ascent has been amazing to see over the past few years. Extensions on chrome allow addition of new features on Chrome made by third party developers. Lately, and there are a few extensions I simply cannot do without. When you need to buckle up and get something done, these extensions will help you get there.</p>

<ol>
<li><p><a href="http://getpocket.com">Pocket</a>:
There are enough interesting things to read on the internet for many lifetimes. Just like youtube's watch it later does for videos, Pocket lets me save articles for future reading. With clients available for iOS and Android, articles saved can be accessed anywhere. At any time on social websites, be it facebook, quora or hacker news, there is a lot I would like to read. Pocket gives me the convenience to customize articles from the internet into my customized feed or magazine via Flipboard integration.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/session-buddy/edacconmaakjimmfgnblocblbcdcpbko?hl=en">Session Buddy</a> :
If you are like me, you context switch a lot between projects during a day. Chrome deals with tabs beautifully, and yet I find myself often with 20 or more tabs, usually researching a particular topic. Usually tabs follow a train of thought but fit within a particular context. Session buddy solves this exact problem, allowing me to save a set of tabs and windows which can be resumed later. For example, at the end of the day at work, I save a bunch of tabs, saved as the name of the project I was working on. This allows me to pick up from the chain of thought from when I left off. Switching between contexts is expensive, and session buddy is the best solution I have found.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.rescuetime.com/">RescueTime</a>:
Holding myself accountable for how I spend time on the web has been eye-opening for me. RescueTime not only tracks how much time during a day you spend on distracting sites, but the desktop application also tracks your non browser time. Over time, it subtly moves you to try and improve your productivity score by avoiding distraction, thus getting more productive (Bravo on the gamification aspect, ResueTime team!) I have discovered patterns of my work through the tool as well, such as the benefits of taking regular breaks and how much standing desk really helps productivity. It however, cannot track that even on productive sites, you can find ways to procrastinate. (I am looking at you, StackOverflow).</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/block-site/eiimnmioipafcokbfikbljfdeojpcgbh?hl=en">Block site</a>:
As much as tracking my time spent on the web helps, sometimes I need to simply block distracting sites. Block site makes for a great complement to RescueTime, allowing me to either visit whitelisted sites only or block off blacklisted sites. I have found my productivity levels on RescueTime spike when using block sites. Often its a reflex action for me to go to facebook or twitter without much thinking. Block sites counts such attempts, and shames you with clever 404 comments. I love that with the latest update, with one switch, you can turn off the distracting websites and focus on the task at hand.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://lastpass.com/">LastPass</a>:
Despite the rise of alternative logins, passwords are still integral parts of the web. With a million sites, having passwords lying around can be rather dangerous. Remembering passwords is time consuming and difficult, adding frustration to the day. LastPass securely stores your passwords for various sites, syncing them across devices. This saves the need to browse through memory trying to dig up a password or worse, store them in flat files. It can also do auto login's for your chosen sites. One of my favorite features is that it warns if you are using duplicate passwords for sites, making your web experience more secure.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://adblockplus.org/en/chrome">Adblock Plus</a>:
Ok, this one is controversial. Adblock will stop advertisements on websites, keeping you focused and saving time particularly for video ads. Now, ads power the web, and any website with ads as primary revenue stream should be aware of adblock. I particularly enjoy the cat and mouse chase between youtube and adblock: youtube refusing to play videos as long as adblock is enabled, adblock gets smarter, youtube catches up. However, it can make certain sites load faster, thus saving time.</p></li>
</ol>


<!-- more -->


<p>Considering how valuable time is, it is important that we get done online what we meant to do. Hopefully, you have discovered an extension or two among this list that you were not aware of before and would help you save some extra time. The better Internet ADD is combated, the more time we spend doing what we love doing or be with family and friends and everybody wins.</p>

<p>This was a post about extensions, but there are certainly tools such as dropbox and evernote which are more than extensions and does boost productivity. If you think there was an extension or tool that I missed, please leave a comment and I would be sure to check it out!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DevsNearMe : July 26-27 Big Data Hackathon]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/07/28/devsnearme-july-26-27-big-data-hackathon/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T12:54:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/07/28/devsnearme-july-26-27-big-data-hackathon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/24686054 " width="595" height="446" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen></iframe> </p>

<p>Built and won the first prize at the big data hackathon at Alley NYC on July 26-27. The goal is to discover how many people are at a venue at a particular point in time and this app will try to do that for hackers, categorized by skills.</p>

<p>With more and more realtime data being available for the public, identifying knowledge clusters at the right point in time becomes really valuable. DevsNearMe is an Android app that attempts to combine data from popular realtime sharing websites such as FourSquare, Twitter, Facebook, Instagram and MeetUp. It will attempts to predict users at a particular location by taking into account absolute numbers, and weighed prediction based on local context based information and learnt knowledge from past user behavior.</p>

<p>This could be highly useful for knowledge sharing, recruiting and demographic analysis. Prototype code is at https://github.com/DevsNearMe .</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Angelhacking at Dumbo]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/06/08/angelhacking-at-dumbo/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-08T16:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/06/08/angelhacking-at-dumbo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>"This is not your ordinary hackathon. This is the big leagues". Such was the claim of Angelhack this past weekend, and two weeks after participating in my first ever serious hackathon, I found myself at another one. There really is something about the mix of meeting cool people, hacking unfamiliar platforms and testing your coding chops in a small amount of time that can be quite addicting.</p>

<p>Shakere, the product I worked on, is an iPhone app for finding people based on skills or interests in social gatherings. Yes, your umpteenth social product, guilty as charged. The space for social discovery really is a heavily contested one, which made me hesitant at first since variants of the idea has been tried by many. I joined however, after realizing that the team would work well together (we actually had a UX designer in the team. Yay!) and this was my chance to experience iOS development, even though I would be developing the backend.</p>

<p>I worked on rolling a RESTful API (https://github.com/shakere/backend), working on the LAMP stack. Though I have not worked too much on LAMP backends before, I must admit that the stack is well suited for rapid prototyping. PHP in particular was a pleasant surprise to work with, in parts because of working with Perl for most of last year. I have had a little stint with Rails, and while Rails seems far more powerful, PHP is more explicit with less magic going on behind the scenes which makes it easier for starters to tinker. However, I did find myself handling quite a few inc files soon and was grepping to find which function was defined where. If I am working on a larger scale PHP project, it would definitely be worth looking into frameworks/best practices for PHP code organization.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img class="left" src="/images/Shakere_Profile.jpg" width="300" height="800" title="Shakere Profile" alt="Shakere Profile"></p>

<p>We got a neat version working well in time for the demo. The app being frontend heavy, I was done with a bit of time in hand, making it a more pleasant hackathon than the last one. Yet during presentation, we did run into the pitfall of not having tested our demo machines to the projector, and this is really a must if you want to avoid delays during your demos.</p>

<p>The ideas were definitely interesting to look at since the hackathon was not restricted to any particular domain. Some were targeting specifically Microsoft, Paypal or Amazon platforms, who were present at the event and provided prizes for the best app using their APIs. It was specifically interesting when domain experts (such as a scientist in a Columbia lab) came to the hackathon trying to device a service for their community. Field experts can have a certain deep understanding of a space and their demos were a good reflection of that.</p>

<p>We did not win unfortunately but judging did seem fair. The ideas winning were generally the apps which were the most mature or demonstrated a clear need base for their ideas. I particularly enjoyed prepared.ly and their combining the job skill-set with learning tools such as Udacity or CodeAcademy. With some personal analytics and initiatives to pick up the skills fast enough, this service can be very useful for coding job seekers.</p>

<p>For the next such event, I would definitely focus more on rolling out more features faster. We were perhaps guilty of actually going around and getting real user data to populate our databases. I would imagine for pre-shipping products you would want this, and MVPs these days certainly value user early user feedback. Hackathons have different needs from production apps though, and rapid feature deployment wins over iterating and getting existing features perfect. You live and you learn.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Publishing Hackathon]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/05/30/publishing-hackathon/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-30T07:08:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/05/30/publishing-hackathon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/Quiply_home.png" width="350" height="350" title="Quiply home" alt="Quiply home"></p>

<p>Alley NYC is a very exciting location that I recently discovered. Its a collaborative workspace for startups, and on weekends they even open their doors for people trying to learn or fine tune their coding skills. On my second visit, I found out about the publishing hackathon, an attempt by the book publishing industry to generate new ideas in a field where profits are seemingly declining. I love books, and it seemed like a good opportunity to see what I could contribute and I signed up.</p>

<p>This past weekend on the day of the hackathon, I arrived early not entirely sure what to expect. There were quite a few volunteers (from the publishing industry sponsors) and mentors (usually the startup founders who work at Alley NYC) and they seemed rather vibrant and chatty, as people in the startup universe tend to be. I immediately found myself talking to several founders about their projects. The breath of industries startups target always fascinate me, but I needed a project.</p>

<p>At the meetup of participants, it seemed like a lot of people came in teamed with ideas they were going to work on or have already been working on. I soon ran into John, who was in the same boat as me in terms of not having a project. John was an UI/UX person, so we thought it would be a good idea to team up and work on something.</p>

<p>The coding part started at noon, and continued for 24 hours. However, it was interesting being developers, we were sought out frequently as the people with ideas outweighed the developers. After discussing a few ideas, we decided on a project. At that moment, we did not expand the team since there was no clear benefit in doing so.</p>

<p>We decided to make Quiply, a book recommendation service aimed at teens based on their online video watching habits. We thought the playlists, favorites and viewing habits of kids gives a good idea of what they are interested in, and giving them small summaries of books they could potentially read to expand on their interests. We decided on making it as a Node js web application to start with, integrating youtube watch history to give results from Amazon.
The rest of the 24 hours, skipping amusing acts by participants which deserve their separate blog post, was a whirlwind of code, coffee, running into hurdles and staggered progress. In the end we managed make the basic prototype work and submitted down to the last minute!</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img class="left" src="/images/Quiply_quip.png" width="500" height="350" title="Quiply quip" alt="Quiply quip"></p>

<p>Here are a few things that I realized at the end of the hackathon, tips to help out a hackathon novice.</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Have a solid idea of what you are going to do even if you do not have a team yet : </strong> A solid worked out plan helps you convince and recruit team members. Hackers by nature are very good readers of someones preparedness, knowledge and value addition to a project, so if you want the good people to team up with you, get in there ready. A very generic idea approaching a unclearly defined problem would likely not get you many co founders. Lot of hackathons do not allow any code being done before the event, but I am not sure how this is implemented since someone could write a library beforehand with quite a bit of logic that they can just import.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Know your apis if you are making an web app : </strong> If you are coding in a hackathon, you want to get to the point where your boilerplate is set up and you are spending the bulk of time building the logic or enhancing the UI. Hence, calling your APIs and knowing the limits and associated delays is critical. For this hackathon, this was not the case for us. After prototyping with youtube, we realized that their APIs no longer allow getting tags from videos and scraping was certainly not an option. We had to switch to Vimeo to get the same functionality. The other problem we ran into was Amazon throttling us for API usage. They had a limit of 2000 requests which we reached fast, and had to create stub accounts to continue testing. Thankfully this was not a problem during our demo, and we were able to show the working app.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Find a good spot quickly with least distractions : </strong> When the participants are not a defined class of people, you get unexpected behaviors and situations that will come up. And once you start coding, these can really harm your productivity. Try to get a nice and quiet place early, and if you find a room with a white board, its a home run for your team.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Keep focused and realistic : </strong> When we started working, I was particularly excited about writing the recommendation engine and wrote out an algorithm to weigh in several factors and generate tiered results based on the particular website queries. (For example, different custom playlists may give us different interests, how the age of the playlist would factor in, etc). However, with the discovery that youtube was not an option, we had to work with Vimeo API which was much limited in terms of features. That resulted in hours of wasted work. Following this setback, we did a better job of focusing hard on getting the one feature of our app working which was getting the recommended books, without much of the initial breadth or depth of the algorithms we were thinking of. Being realistic about what was achievable in 24 hours allowed us to get a working prototype, and this is very important in hackathons where wealth of APIs and possibilities can hinder your progress.</p></li>
</ol>


<p><img class="right" src="/images/Quiply_login.png" width="400" height="350" title="Quiply login" alt="Quiply login"></p>

<p>There were an interesting array of projects presented, some more matured than others by virtue of being worked on before. But they were mostly web apps or mobile apps, simply because that is what most developers are working on these days. We were not one of the finalists, but overall I was very glad to reach and idea, and generate a fully working app within the 24 hours and it was a whole lot of fun! I would absolutely do more hackathons from now on, just not every weekend.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
