<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Flask | Avi Das]]></title>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/categories/flask/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2022-08-14T17:45:46-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://avidas.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Avi (Ananya Das)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Evaluating React.js and Flask]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2015/08/05/evaluating-react-dot-js-and-flask/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-05T10:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2015/08/05/evaluating-react-dot-js-and-flask</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Update: Udemy has generously granted a free coupon for the readers of this blog for their <a href="https://www.udemy.com/learn-and-understand-reactjs/learn/">React JS and Flux</a> course. Use the code <code>avidasreactjs</code> and the first 50 readers will get free access to the course!</p></blockquote>

<p>As a connoisseur of the web, front-end frameworks have been been a fertile area of late. React.js from Facebook has taken much fanfare, and this post evaluates key ideas on react, and digs into why you could be interested in React. Staying true to single responsibility principle, React is a highly useful tool if you are doing web programming.</p>

<p>In this post, we will dive into building a Frontend using React.js and Backend built using the Python framework Flask. Flask is a minimalistic framework, and excellent when your backend becomes more and more of an API. Moreover, this facilitates the microservices architecture, where the decoupling of your your app into small unit of services can make it more maintainable and scalable.</p>

<p>We will cover some of the key ideas of React and Flask here, but it would be worth referring to the official documentation for <a href="https://facebook.github.io/react/">React</a> and <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/">Flask</a> for getting started and understanding the philosophies of each framework.</p>

<h3>Key Ideas of React</h3>

<p>The core idea of React is the developers are better of leaving manipulating the DOM to battle tested framework code. Since the DOM has a tree structure, finding elements and manipulating them would need many traversals of a potentially very large tree.  Instead, what you modify is a virtual DOM, and React runs its intelligent diffing algorithm to directly update the DOM.</p>

<h5>React</h5>

<p>React itself is the UI library that will manage all the DOM updates as data changes. It's takes the V of MVC frameworks, hence it can be used with other MVC frameworks such as Angular, Backbone or Meteor. It is quite easy to use React to manage specific areas of your application's UI, rather than the entire app.</p>

<h5>Virtual Dom</h5>

<p>The virtual Dom is an abstraction layer between nodes in the real DOM and the view of the code you are modifying. When React selectively renders subtrees of the nodes in DOM based upon state changes, it achieves the following</p>

<pre><code> 1. Ensures that your DOM is always up to date with current state
 2. Reduces the need to re-render the DOM every time there is change in state
 3. Updating only the individual components on state change ensures high performance
</code></pre>

<h5>JSX</h5>

<p>JSX is a JavaScript syntax extension and it brings in a HTML/XML like familiar syntax for defining a tree structure with attributes. This is the syntax you can use to declare the changes in layout code and React will update the UI. It's a bold approach, since developers are conditioned to keep layout code separate from Javascript. We will explain more React terminology later as we dive into some code.</p>

<h3>Key Ideas of Flask</h3>

<p>Flask is a microframework, which means that it trades a short learning curve for fewer out of the box functionalities, compared to heavier frameworks such as Django or Rails. It gives developers more freedom to use their preferable tools and libraries. However, it does have a list of officially supported <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/extensions/">extensions</a> which when plugged in provide a wide breath of functionalities for a standard web app. Extensions behave as if they are native flask code.</p>

<p>We strongly recommend that you set up a <a href="http://www.virtualenv.org/">virtualenv</a> for this project, and you may also want to check out <a href="http://virtualenvwrapper.readthedocs.org/">virtualenvwrapper</a> for convenience. This is to provide your app with a sandboxed environment.</p>

<h5>Getting up and running with Flask</h5>

<p>Lets first install Flask</p>

<p>```bash
pip install Flask</p>

<h1>For viewing and reusing app dependencies</h1>

<p>pip freeze > requirements.txt
```
Set up the following directory structure in your app.</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<p>├── README.md
├── app.py
├── requirements.txt
└── templates</p>

<pre><code>└── index.html
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Modify your app.py code to include the following</p>

<p>```python
from flask import Flask, render_template</p>

<p>app = Flask(<strong>name</strong>)</p>

<p>@app.route("/")</p>

<p>def index():</p>

<pre><code>return render_template('index.html')
</code></pre>

<p>if <strong>name</strong> == "<strong>main</strong>":</p>

<pre><code>app.run()
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>We start by importing Flask and creating a new instance of a flask application. In flask, app.route is used to describe the behavior when users hit particular endpoints in the application. Here when user hits the index route, we render a template called hello world. By default Flask uses the Jinja2 templating language, but you can use any other templating language. In fact, we will not be covering Jinja2 in this blog post. Finally we tell python to call the run method of the app when invoked as a main function.</p>

<p>Let's populate index.html with the following basic HTML boilerplate</p>

<p>```html</p>

<p>&lt;!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head></p>

<pre><code>&lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Flask React Tutorial&lt;/title&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></head>
<body></p>

<pre><code> &lt;div id="mount-point"&gt;
     &lt;p1&gt;Hello world.&lt;/p1&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></body>
</html>
```</p>

<p>Now run the app with</p>

<p><code>bash
python app.py
// * Running on http://127.0.0.0:5000/
// * Restarting with reloader
</code>
By default it runs on port 5000. Navigate to the endpoint and you should see the html page you just created. You are now up and running with Flask!</p>

<h5>Integrate React</h5>

<p>Easiest way to include React would be to just include them from a cdn. Let's update the index.html to include React and and port our existing html to React. index.html will now look like</p>

<p>```html</p>

<p>&lt;!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head></p>

<pre><code>&lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Flask React Tutorial&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;script src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/react/0.13.2/react.min.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/react/0.13.2/JSXTransformer.js"&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></head>
<body></p>

<pre><code> &lt;div id="mount-point"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></body></p>

<p>  <script type="text/jsx"></p>

<pre><code> /*** @jsx React.DOM */
var FirstComponent = React.createClass({
    render: function() {
        return (&lt;p1&gt;Hello world.&lt;/p1&gt;);
    }
});
React.render(&lt;FirstComponent /&gt;, document.getElementById('mount-point') );
 &lt;/script&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></html>
```</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Let's go over the code. We first include the react and jsx libraries via the script tags and remove the earlier p tags. We set up a jsx script by specifying type="text/jsx". Then we call createClass method of React which creates a React component. React components are reusable units that you can use to compose your UI. The component must have at least the render method, which returns the virtual representation of a native DOM element or another component.
Next we call React.render with the first element and pass it the id of the div element on which we want the result of the render function to be. Run the app again to navigate to the same path to see the app again.</p>

<h5>Data binding with React</h5>

<p>For a more practical example, as well to demonstrate multiple components, let's produce a type along data binding example. You can replace your script tag with the following</p>

<p>```html</p>

<script type="text/jsx">
    /** @jsx React.DOM */
    var Input = React.createClass({
        updateLabel: function(event){
            this.setState({value: event.target.value});
        },
        getInitialState: function(){
            return {
                value: ''
            }
        },
        componentWillMount: function(){
            this.setState({value: this.state.value})
        },
        render: function(){
            return (
                <div className="update-label">
                      <input type="text" placeholder="Enter text" onChange={this.updateLabel}/>
                    <Label value={this.state.value}/>
                </div>
        )
    }
});

var Label = React.createClass({
    render: function(){
        return (
        <div class="my-label">
        <h2>{this.props.value}</h2>
        </div>
        )
    }
});

React.render(<Input/>, document.getElementById('mount-point'));
</script>


<p>```</p>

<p>As before, React.render is called at the very end on a component called Input and it is bound to the element with id mount-point. Inside the Input component a few other lifecycle functions are introduced.</p>

<p>The method getInitialState is called once before the component mounts and  responsible for setting for the initial state of a component.
componentWillMount is called directly before a react component is initially rendered. Inside componentWillMount, we invoke setState.</p>

<p>setState can trigger UI updates from event handlers and server request callbacks. It will always cause a re-render to happen. Once render is called, it returns a div with a input box and a React component called label. We attach the method updateLabel which gets invoked when the text inside the input box changes. It updates this.state.value.</p>

<p>State attributes are mutable within a component and are used to represent the interaction changes changes within a component. On the other hand, props are immutable and used to pass data from a parent component to a child. In this case Label is a child component of Input, and this.state.value for Input is passed to Label, which can access it by this.props.value. Thus Input passes the data entered into the input box to Label and causes it to re-render and display the text.</p>

<p>Fire up the server again and type something into the input box and the content gets updated in the h2 element underneath.</p>

<h5>Why React</h5>

<p>As it turns out, the selling points of React are not super hard to get and clear use cases became obvious.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>React is very efficient in the way it handles DOM updates. It is important however, to isolate that heavy rendering or interactions are the bottlenecks so that you are not optimizing prematurely and likely already have optimized database interactions and network calls.</p></li>
<li><p>SEO management overhead can be less with React compared to Angular/Ember since it can be rendered server side. The benefit comes from not having the overhead of rendering your page server side with something like PhantomJS and serving the HTML.</p></li>
<li><p>Reusable components make the code more reusable and testable, and the short terminology keeps the learning curve managable.</p></li>
<li><p>Since React can be rendered Server Side, you might completely get rid of your server side templating, further reducing the number of tools necessary to run your app.</p></li>
</ol>


<h5>React and Flask</h5>

<p>With their focus on SRP, React and Flask could be dependable and efficient parts of your stack. This is specially handy if you want to leverage the Numpy/Scipy stack for doing data analysis in near realtime and serve up a frontend with heavy user interaction. In a later post, we will look at exploring interactive applications and introduce Socket.io.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Connected car: Meticulous.io @Angelhack]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2014/01/07/connected-car-at-angelhack/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-07T23:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2014/01/07/connected-car-at-angelhack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Angelhack looks for startups to come out of hackathons rather than just weekend hacks. As a result, it tends to get very product driven as teams compete for the Angelpad recognition. The theme this year was Apphack, and mobile apps were the key focus. Not really a surprise, as more and more startups build mobile first.</p>

<p>We worked on the verizon telematics data. <a href="http://www.verizontelematics.com/">Verizon telematics</a> is something I did not know about before. Car companies have been working with Verizon to install a device in the cars that could send data about speed, location, rpm, condition of the car in terms of last time since gas, particular model of car, wear and tear to the cloud. I expect Verizon is able to collect a lot more than the columns we saw. Needless to say, this would be a very powerful dataset and it is surprising that there aren't more going on in this space.</p>

<p><a href="http://ipython.org/">iPython</a> and <a href="http://pandas.pydata.org/">Pandas</a> are built for analyzing and visualizing tabular data like this. Questions such as which brand of car gave the best milage per gallon, which brand was driven more on the highway vs which was more popular on the city roads were fairly easy to answer. It was not clear if the data given to us was indeed an uniform sample, but results were interesting. However, they are hardly hackathon worthy ideas.</p>

<p>Needed an idea. One set of data had trip ids tied to driver ids, the other set had per trip latitudes and longitudes. Aggregating them somehow would be interesting. Geographical history of most visited places can be found since trips could be tied to drivers. Historical driving records could be obtained from individual trips and the overall history of the driver measured. Global driving records could be obtained so that the best driver's can be found.</p>

<p>Once noting those features, the next step was to think how this would make sense as a product. Context sensitive software is hugely in demand and this is a great dataset for revealing patterns of drivers. Buisnesses aware of customers frequenting particular location can push deals and coupons to those individuals to drive buisness. Timeliness of visit can be used to fine tune the deals even more, e.g. lunch deals would make sense around the Grand Central area in NYC to a busy professional. The brand of car can be used to push vehicle specific ads. This would also be a treasure trove of information for car insurance companies figuring out insurance rates. Finally, it is quite possible that driving patterns can be used to trigger alert that may detect an accident ahead of time.</p>

<p>Its hard to argue that driving patterns are valuable data. However, as with any user specific information used for personalization experiences curated by businesses, privacy would be a big concern. It was not entirely clear who would own the data, the driver, the provider, or else. It should be made very clear to the driver of the nature of the tracking going on and how the data may be used. Since data like this could easily be used by a malicious third party to monitor you in real time when you are driving, there is inherent danger in it being available without the driver being informed. Tracking is an issue users of any clowd aware system needs to be aware of.</p>

<p>We did win the Verizon prize for the hackathon, and it was nice having our idea at the eleventh hour being well accepted. Angelhack put on a good show, and I must mention the apps "Make it Rain" (literally, on the phone screen) and "Kanye"(alerts if you are nearby Kanye West) for the hilarity during the presentation!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DevsNearMe : July 26-27 Big Data Hackathon]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/07/28/devsnearme-july-26-27-big-data-hackathon/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T12:54:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2013/07/28/devsnearme-july-26-27-big-data-hackathon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/24686054 " width="595" height="446" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen></iframe> </p>

<p>Built and won the first prize at the big data hackathon at Alley NYC on July 26-27. The goal is to discover how many people are at a venue at a particular point in time and this app will try to do that for hackers, categorized by skills.</p>

<p>With more and more realtime data being available for the public, identifying knowledge clusters at the right point in time becomes really valuable. DevsNearMe is an Android app that attempts to combine data from popular realtime sharing websites such as FourSquare, Twitter, Facebook, Instagram and MeetUp. It will attempts to predict users at a particular location by taking into account absolute numbers, and weighed prediction based on local context based information and learnt knowledge from past user behavior.</p>

<p>This could be highly useful for knowledge sharing, recruiting and demographic analysis. Prototype code is at https://github.com/DevsNearMe .</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
