<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Growth | Avi Das]]></title>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/categories/growth/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-05-09T16:23:07-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://avidas.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Avi (Ananya Das)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quotes I have loved]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2020/05/06/favorite-quotes/"/>
    <updated>2020-05-06T12:51:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2020/05/06/favorite-quotes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A brilliant and succint quote that says so much about our being.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The negativity bias is a well intentioned learning disability.</p><footer><strong>Tara Brach</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Two quotes from the best book I have ever read.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Everything can be taken from a man but one thing: the last of the human freedoms—to choose one’s attitude in any given set of circumstances, to choose one’s own way.</p></p><p><p>Between stimulus and response there is a space. In that space is our power to choose our response. In our response lies our growth and our freedom.</p><footer><strong>Viktor Frankl</strong> <cite>Man's Search for Meaning</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I have been a long time admirer of the way Feynman lived his life.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The first principle is that you must not fool yourself, and you are the easiest person to fool.</p><footer><strong>Richard Feynman</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Anais Nin should be more well known.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Life shrinks or expands in proportion to one's courage.</p><footer><strong>Anais Nin</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><a href="https://nav.al/">Naval</a> may be the most quotable person around today.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><blockquote><p>Desire is a contract that you make with yourself to be unhappy until you get what you want.</p></p><p><p>It is the mark of a charlatan to explain a simple concept in a complex way and it is the mark of a genius to explain a complex topic in a simple way.</p><footer><strong>Naval Ravikant</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Often quoted to JFK, this quote originated in the early 19th century.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The rising tide lifts all boats.</p><footer><strong>The [New York] Christian Advocate</strong> <cite>Never Paralleled in New York</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Insight into how running can be a source of meaning.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>It's not something most human beings would give a moment of consideration to, that it is actually possible to be living for years in a state of constant betterment.  To consider that you are better today than you were yesterday or a year ago, and that you will be better still tomorrow or next week or at tournament time your senior year.  That if you're doing it right you are an organism constantly evolving toward some agreed-upon approximation of excellence.  Wouldn't that be at least one definition of a spiritual state?</p><footer><strong>John L. Parker Jr</strong> <cite>Again to Carthage</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/just_breathe.jpg" width="500" height="500" title="Breathe" alt="Breathe"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
