<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Life | Avi Das]]></title>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2022-08-14T17:48:33-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://avidas.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Avi (Ananya Das)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quotes I have loved]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2020/05/06/favorite-quotes/"/>
    <updated>2020-05-06T12:51:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2020/05/06/favorite-quotes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A brilliant and succint quote that says so much about our being.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The negativity bias is a well intentioned learning disability.</p><footer><strong>Tara Brach</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Two quotes from the best book I have ever read.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Everything can be taken from a man but one thing: the last of the human freedoms—to choose one’s attitude in any given set of circumstances, to choose one’s own way.</p></p><p><p>Between stimulus and response there is a space. In that space is our power to choose our response. In our response lies our growth and our freedom.</p><footer><strong>Viktor Frankl</strong> <cite>Man's Search for Meaning</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I have been a long time admirer of the way Feynman lived his life.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The first principle is that you must not fool yourself, and you are the easiest person to fool.</p><footer><strong>Richard Feynman</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Anais Nin should be more well known.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Life shrinks or expands in proportion to one's courage.</p></p><p><p>We write to taste life twice, in the moment and in retrospection. We write, like Proust, to render all of it eternal, and to persuade ourselves that it is eternal. We write to be able to transcend our life, to reach beyond it.</p><footer><strong>Anais Nin</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><a href="https://nav.al/">Naval</a> may be the most quotable person around today.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><blockquote><p>Desire is a contract that you make with yourself to be unhappy until you get what you want.</p></p><p><p>It is the mark of a charlatan to explain a simple concept in a complex way and it is the mark of a genius to explain a complex topic in a simple way.</p></p><p><p>A busy mind and a busy calendar will destroy your ability to create anything great.</p><footer><strong>Naval Ravikant</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Often quoted to JFK, this quote originated in the early 19th century.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The rising tide lifts all boats.</p><footer><strong>The [New York] Christian Advocate</strong> <cite>Never Paralleled in New York</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><blockquote><p>We don't rise to the level of our expectations, we fall to the level of our training.</p><footer><strong>Archilochus</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Insight into how running can be a source of meaning.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>It's not something most human beings would give a moment of consideration to, that it is actually possible to be living for years in a state of constant betterment.  To consider that you are better today than you were yesterday or a year ago, and that you will be better still tomorrow or next week or at tournament time your senior year.  That if you're doing it right you are an organism constantly evolving toward some agreed-upon approximation of excellence.  Wouldn't that be at least one definition of a spiritual state?</p><footer><strong>John L. Parker Jr</strong> <cite>Again to Carthage</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/just_breathe.jpg" width="500" height="500" title="Breathe" alt="Breathe"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thriving Under Siege]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2020/04/12/thriving-under-siege/"/>
    <updated>2020-04-12T20:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2020/04/12/thriving-under-siege</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Besieged</em></p>

<p>That one word captures the reality of living in NYC during the Covid-19 pandemic. It feels like being surrounded by an invisible, encroaching army, with no end to the siege in sight.</p>

<p>Everyday we are exposed to terrible news, how <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/09/nyregion/coronavirus-queens-corona-jackson-heights-elmhurst.html">immigrants are hurting in my beloved Jackson Heights neighborhood</a>, mass burial grounds either locally or abroad in Italy and China. Bustling businesses in NYC have been reduced to laying off hard working employees.</p>

<p>There is no how-to manual for this current crisis, so devastating and foreign to all of us. Despite that, resilience is human nature. If there's one place where our collective faiths have met, it is that better times are ahead. Is the thought of thriving during the age of Covid-19 heretical? It is perhaps more so to not attempt to.</p>

<p>Like many others, I have struggled with being quarantined in my apartment since March. I have immersed myself with the energy and drive that permeates NYC, and losing that has felt like being in withdrawal. At times, it has been a fearsome cocktail of loneliness, helplessness and concern.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/alone.jpg" width="500" height="500" title="Alone" alt="Alone"></p>

<p>I am a rational optimist. I like to think that better times can be ahead, but we have to strive towards it.  While my framework of life has been shaken by this crisis, it has yet to be broken, and it has definitely opened up more opportunities for self discovery.</p>

<p>Thanks to the internet, social media and on demand entertainment, simply passing time has stopped being a challenge. Rather, boredom has been a foreign concept to many of us surfing the world of dopamine rushes. Yet, deep inside, many of us feel that they fail to aid deep seated needs of purpose and self-actualization.</p>

<p>So how do we deal with our current consternation? Can we come out on the other side of this and be proud of what these last months meant for us? When we look back into this in five years, how will we think of this time?</p>

<p><strong>Invest in community</strong></p>

<p>It's more important than ever to be there for your friends and family. Deepening relationships with our closest people have a way of giving back to our lives. That could just be video chats, and I have noticed myself talking to my folks a lot more since this began. There was also one night when, after some silly games on the House Party app, I realized I haven't laughed this hard in a while and how necessary that was.</p>

<p><strong>Continue voting for your best self</strong></p>

<p>As the dust settled and I got more used to realizing that this is my life for the foreseeable future, I wanted to dig into things I could do but have been putting off due to the <strong>busy-ness</strong> of life. Not being as busy can be a positive thing, and opens up more time for things I have wanted to do more of.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Since Quarantine began, I have finished three books, and have enjoyed the process of being engrossed in a book more than usual, now that the usual societal stimulation has been removed. Using this time to read books I have been meaning to for a while has been enjoyable, accepting the mental escape that literature offers.</p>

<p>Cooking has added a lot of value to my life in the past, being able to create something nourishing that is beautiful and delicious is a very fulfilling act. I have been cooking more than I have been in a while and been really enjoying it. A good side effect of this is has been generally eating better since Quarantine.</p>

<p>Even before quarantine began, I have been coming off a challenging period in my life. Meditation has been the place I have been going to find center and grounding. It has also been fulfilling to keep a meditation streak of over 100 days and the reinforcement that just breathing can encapsulate all existence is powerful knowledge.</p>

<p>Life is not a scorecard, and the above activities are not things I do to achieve anything other than that I know my best self would enjoy. Even though they can be hard to start, they always make me feel better afterwards.</p>

<p><strong>Use this as an opportunity for greater self-discovery</strong></p>

<p>If you are on your own, you can truly choose how to spend a lot of your time. For myself, this has revealed for me that I thrive when there is human connection. Quarantine meant physical proximity has not been an option, but it has made me think about the key allies in my life, reaching out, resulting often in deeper conversations.</p>

<p>Creativity is important to my life, but it is stifled unless there is a stable base. An organized desk, a clean room and decorating my room so I can see artifacts that remind myself of my best times are actions I have doubled down on. Sleeping more is another such act, and I have given myself the license to sleep as much as I need.</p>

<p>I firmly believe that self-actualization is the modern day superpower. As someone who has a long way to go on that journey, this is our time for digging  deep. Whether it is seeking internally via meditation or solo walks, or externally by reading or deep conversations, may this time help us on that journey.</p>

<p><strong>Pursue acts of spirituality</strong></p>

<p><blockquote><p>It's not something most human beings would give a moment of consideration to, that it is actually possible to be living for years in a state of constant betterment.  To consider that you are better today than you were yesterday or a year ago, and that you will be better still tomorrow or next week or at tournament time your senior year.  That if you're doing it right you are an organism constantly evolving toward some agreed-upon approximation of excellence.  Wouldn't that be at least one definition of a spiritual state?</p></p><p><ul><br/><li>Again to Carthage, John L. Parker, Jr</p></blockquote></li>
</ul>


<p>The above is an excerpt from one of my favorite passages of writing. It has really touched the cord on why running has been a constant in my life over the last six years. Movement and running is essential for me at a subliminal level, and pursuing it is more of an act of spirituality than chasing personal records, experiencing the spectacle of a Marathon Major or accumulating mileage.</p>

<p>When I mention the word spirituality, I mean those acts that you follow with conviction whether or not an ulterior motive is involved. I have noticed that dancing plays that role for a lot of people as well. Whether it is running, dance or prayer, pursuing them can water a deeper part of us.</p>

<p><strong>Practice self forgiveness</strong></p>

<p>It's important to not beat yourself over achieving goals, especially during this time. Comparing ourselves to a few selected people who achieved great acts of invention during times of trial is not a healthy activity.</p>

<p>In the same vein, there may be guilt which stems from the nagging feeling that you are not doing enough, that we could do more. It's wonderful how some of us have risen to the needs and led efforts for mask production, test kit distribution etc, but those are not the only ways to add value to others.</p>

<p>Where we will end up is unknown, but isn't that always the case? Existential threats and uncertainty can add a lot of suffering to our lives. Suffering is a side effect of being alive, but it is not where the goalpost is. Choosing to thrive in these times, taking actions that vote towards that direction and continue nurturing our deepest selves are some of the best things we can do in these times. I sincerely hope that manifests for you, dear reader.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sunset_alone.jpg" width="550" height="550" title="Sunset Alone" alt="Sunset Alone"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Life lessons from Improv]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2019/03/16/life-lessons-from-doing-improv/"/>
    <updated>2019-03-16T15:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2019/03/16/life-lessons-from-doing-improv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think life should be more like improv and improv should resemble life.</p>

<p>On a whim, I went to hideout theatre in Austin, TX for a improv beginner class back in 2016 but I have only been consistently doing improv for the past year. In the process, I have tried short and long form improv, and dabbled in musical/rap improv. Having zero theatre/stage background, it has been amazing to me how the lessons learnt from improv apply to life broadly.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/improv.jpg" width="350" height="350" title="Improv" alt="Improv"></p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Yes, and..</strong>: A 101 on improv would begin with the encouragement to accept whatever the other person is bringing to the scene. We may have a great idea in mind, but the scene is ruined if we do not accept the other person's ideas and bind the scene in a cohesive way. Taking this attitude to life can frame anything in life as a gift. This in turns lends us to be less critical and cynical about our day to day interactions.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Go with the first thing that comes to mind</strong>: Perfect is often the enemy of the good. Overthinking can stand in the way of action when spontaneity may have been the right choice. In improv, trying to think of a funny punchline can ruin an act, taking away from it the natural flow of the scene. On the other hand, going with the first thing that comes to mind often leads a scene to wonderful surprises. Real life decisions do involve more thought, but the training against overthinking still holds and can help us live a more spontaneous life and overcome the fear of taking action.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Embracing failure</strong>: Making a fool of yourself is encouraged and celebrated in improv. The very act of complete unpreparedness on stage, taking the audience's suggestion to theme a scene and strangers as partners means that you don't have any semblance of control. There is no guarantee that an improv scene will be funny to the audience or reach a satisfying closure. But everyone in improv understands this, and supports your choices on stage regardless. This empowers improvisers to be authentic on stage. It also makes us realize that the consequences of failure may be less than we realize. This training is so important in life where fear of failure can hold us back.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Make others look good</strong>: In improv, we succeed when we have made the others on stage successful. Supporting their ideas, pointing out the authenticity of their actions and emotions goes a long way into making a scene feel natural and relatable to the audience. When working with improvisers who are gifted in building out storylines, a great way to complement their work is to add other dimensions to the scene such as a location, timeline or other context to create a richer, vivid scene. This prioritizing of win-win mentality is a great habit for teams, since an effective team should be greater than the sum of its individuals.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Make statements, don't ask questions</strong>:
Making statements adds material to a scene, whereas a question puts the burden on the other to come up with the material. This is why it is encouraged in improv to limit questions and respond with statements. This is great for your communication skills, making conversations feel less like interrogations. People feel more at ease in a conversation when they feel they don't have to do all the work. A related advice is to try and use every sentence in improv as if it would be a closing sentence, since a scene could end at any moment. <!-- more --></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Leading with emotions</strong>:
An audience is watching an improv scene has a fuller experience when they not only hear the words but see the emotions of the performers. Life is certainly more complicated. If you are investing in the stock market or playing poker, it is best to distrust or hide your emotions. On the other hand, lot of us lack the ability to emote even when situations demand it, because our upbringing has taught us to treat display of emotions as weakness. Improv can help unlearn and be more expressive in situations when we should lead with our emotions.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Take the scene somewhere</strong>: In an improv scene, you and your partner create a character and a world which has the shelf life of the scene. The scene can be as short as a minute and half. It is great for the audience when the scene builds up to something, has a beginning, middle and end. In the movie of our lives, we are the protagonists living our story. The practice of improv helps us build a viewpoint of our lives from a third party perspective, and can make us wonder how we want the protagonist to act. To use a computing analogy, it would be similar to seeing life from a debug mode.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Listen</strong>: There simply cannot be a good scene where you ignore the words, behavior and actions of your partner. Improv helps emphasize the importance of listening, the power of which is well understood.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Have fun</strong>: The audience knows when the performers are enjoying themselves, and can feel they are part of it too.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Commit to a scene</strong>: A more experienced improviser advised me to commit with your voice, face and your body. The practice of complete immersion in a scene can help us be more present when we show up in life.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>The beauty of improv is that you don't have to become a great improviser to see the positive effects it can have on your life. Those of us who believe in constant improvement and are interested in living a more examined life and will find improv valuable.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/improv2.jpg" width="500" height="500" title="Improv Last" alt="Improv Last"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
