<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Tech | Avi Das]]></title>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/categories/tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://avidas.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-04-18T22:07:32-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://avidas.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Avi (Ananya Das)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mindsets for Tech Behavioral Interviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://avidas.github.com/blog/2020/03/07/on-tech-behavioral-interviews/"/>
    <updated>2020-03-07T13:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://avidas.github.com/blog/2020/03/07/on-tech-behavioral-interviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Axiom: Any software engineer writing a blog on tech will eventually write a post about interviews. - Yours Truly</em></p>

<p>You walk into a room with one or two people, who may be taking notes in a notepad or a laptop. The most common starter question is <em>tell me about yourself</em>.</p>

<p>This used to be a question I didn't know where to start or end. A possible interpretation of this question is to provide a succinct summary of your career.</p>

<p>The opportunity here is to prime the interviewer towards directions which would highlight your best career experiences. What part of your experience would be the most pertinent for this job? Doing this thinking beforehand would be helpful for the latter part of the interview.</p>

<p>As an interviewee, we are selling ourselves during an interview. For engineers, this is not a natural part of our workflow. The best sales, however, are based on truth. Being honest and talking proudly about your best career achievements will aid you in this early phase.</p>

<p>A very common follow up is <em>what your ideal next role would look like</em>? You've just given them the path which got you to where you are. It is now time to lay out what you want for the future.</p>

<p>The opportunity in this question to highlight areas where you want to grow. Do you see yourself going into engineering management? Do you want to become really good at javascript and browsers? Or do you prefer to become an expert in server and cluster management? Again, it serves you to be honest here since this question helps you to evaluate if the growth opportunities you are looking for would be possible at this company.</p>

<p><em>Go in with a win-win mentality: It is a lot more about finding a mutual fit rather than getting through a cross examination.</em></p>

<p>After this point, the interview can go in a lot of different directions. Companies may dig deeper into your past experience or go through example scenarios to understand your  thinking process. Knowing your resume and being able to talk in depth about each part will be important.</p>

<p>Good luck with your interview process!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
